<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A newe discourse of morall philosophie, entituled, The kayes of counsaile Not so pleasant as profitable for younge courtiours. Optima est patientia victor.</title>
            <author>Heron, Haly.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03100</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108570</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844228</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844228</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9019</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03100)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9019)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 547:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A newe discourse of morall philosophie, entituled, The kayes of counsaile Not so pleasant as profitable for younge courtiours. Optima est patientia victor.</title>
                  <author>Heron, Haly.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 143 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by [H. Bynneman for] Ralph Newberie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1579.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The title has a punning reference to the dedicatee, John Kay the younger.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Slight print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9019:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9019:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NEWE Diſcourſe of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Philoſophie, <hi>Entituled,</hi>
               </hi> The Kayes of Counſaile.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not ſo pleaſant as profitable, for younge Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Optima est Patientia Victor.</q>
            <p>AT LONDON, Imprinted by Ralph Newberie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno.</hi> 1579.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:9019:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Jndex.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Of humilitie.</label> Cap. 1</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of company &amp; felovvſhip.</label> Ca. 2.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of talke &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication.</label> Ca. 3.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of modeſt behauiour.</label> Cap. 4.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of ſelfe loue.</label> Cap. 5.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of vvine and vvomen.</label> Cap. 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of dyce play.</label> Cap. 7.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of trauaile.</label> Cap. 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of ſtabilitie.</label> Cap. 9.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9019:2"/>
            <head>To John Kay the younger <hi>Gent. Haly Heron his Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> wiſheth continuall health, with increaſe of learnyng and vertues.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I had well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with my ſelf how great affinities are ſayd to be betwixt learning and good maners, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as either of them without the other ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be vnperfect, &amp; both equally ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. (O God) how ſtraight a courſe they take to wyn both worldly fauour &amp; eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall felicitie: I haue thought good, as well preſently nouriſhing thy tender wittes by dayly inſtruction, as hereafter (when ſome priuate occaſion may perhaps remoue me from thy company) to leaue theſe fewe preceptes of morall Philoſophie togither, with my eſpeciall good will towards thee bent, in riper yeares of diſcretion to be well wayed and ſeriouſly folowed. The gifts of nature which appeare in the bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes
<pb facs="tcp:9019:3"/>
of youth, ſo bountifully beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, haue (as it were by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) allured mee to giue theſe inſtructions of Courtly behauior, not bicauſe I wold ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by perſuade thee to ſeeke ſuche doubtfull preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but (if hereafter by the good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of thy parents thou be commaunded, or by deceiptful emulation drawen to ſuch kinde of ſeruice) that thou mighteſt in the entrance of ſo perillous a paſſage, be well armed againſt thoſe daungerous delights which vnto others for want of better go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, hath bene the chiefe cauſe of ruinous decayes and skornful ouerthrow. And firſt I woulde haue thee to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, that the Court is a boyſterous Sea, where by the raging ſtormes aboue head, the ſtrongeſt ſhippes are throwen vpon the doubtfull rockes of diſpleaſure, and yet ſometymes by the fauourable aſpecte of fortune, ſafely ariued in the quiet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of good happe. It is like a ſteepe hyll or huge mountayne harde for any man to clymbe, and yet apt for all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eaſily from thence to fall downe headlong, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb facs="tcp:9019:3"/>
to ſuch as are ſwifteſt of foote, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lighteſt of heade, nothing ſubiect to good counſel &amp; foreſight of miſchiefs. The wayes are pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the enterteinme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſweet, but the felowſhip is the more doubtful, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that vnder ſo ſweete a taſt oft tymes lie many bitter pilles of hard digeſtion, and as ſome ſay, the common ſickneſſe of the Court, is to ſurfeyt in the ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kets of diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling: but no man can burne his fingers without fyre, nor be deceyued where hee hath not ouermuch truſted. Moreouer, the way to vice is readily founde, but the true path and footeſteppes of Vertue not ſo eaſie to be folowed: For nature is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to ſinne, and ſoone allured by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticements of follie, but noble Vertue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth longer tymes of increaſe, whoſe humble roote as it were by degrees ſpred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hir ſelfe abroade, is the more ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye planted in the firme grounde of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect knowledge, where not by kinde, but cuſtomablye increaſing, bringeth foorth the flowers of worthie fame, and ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne fruites of felicitie. Thys is the
<pb facs="tcp:9019:4"/>
marke whereat all men ſhould leuell, and the boundes of humaine life which by no meanes can be enlarged: and as by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of nature we are all moued with a prouident care to liue (as by the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of pleaſures and needefull commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of life it is manifeſt) ſo muche more ought we by reaſon ſeriouſly to ſeeke the ſafe conduct of vertue, that guideth vs di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to the Pallace of eternall life and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting pleaſures: by this we haue fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with Angels in heauen, after the conſummation of this tragicall act, but the other is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to vs with all other earthly creatures. Take therefore theſe inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of vertue for a newe yeares gift at my handes, which (alluding to thy name) I haue entituled <hi>the Keyes of Counſaile:</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, the eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as by the prouidence of God and the furtherance of good parents here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, thine eſtate may be worthily aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: ſo that the daungerous courſe &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures of youth by theſe my trauayles ſhalbe the better directed and more ſafely gouerned. I haue folowed the praiſe of
<pb facs="tcp:9019:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
vertue more than the reprehenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vice, in this ſhort diſcourſe of maners, for that with <hi>Cicero</hi> the Prince of eloquence, I hold it greater glorie that is gotten by defence of honeſtie, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is doubtfully receiued by diſcloſing of miſdeedes. If want of skill hath vnpleaſauntlye cloſed vp the wyde fields of rethorical exornations in ſo good a matter, accept the morall ſenſe of ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, which tendeth rather to plaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, than vaine pleaſure: But if perhaps the diſcourſe ſeeme to be ſhorter than the greedie mindes and attentiue eares of the ſtudious herein ſhould require, content thy ſelfe, that the reſt of my winter exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe hath bene applied to thine owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate inſtruction. Farewell, and thus much remember: That life without learning is vnpleaſant, and learning without vertues vnprofitable. Cal. Decemb. 1578.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Gouernour for the tyme, and thy friende for euer. <hi>HALY HERON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9019:5"/>
            <head>Of Humilitie.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſtrong foundations of vertue grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded on Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, muſt of force his raiſed from the ſtedfaſte rocke of Faith: For as it is by true recorde of holy ſcriptures witneſſed, <hi>The feare of God is the beginning of wiſedome.</hi> And ſurelie when a man begins to conſider the frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of fleſhe, and immortalitie of the ſoule, the miſerable calamities of this worlde, and the ineſtimable, ioyes of heauen, of mankind the vaine folly, and the true per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of diuine nature and omnipotencie of God: Euen then is he tryed with the touchſtone of trueth, or rather moued by the ſuggeſtion of holy ſpirit, to feare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſt iudgement of the almightie, miſtruſting his owne righteouſneſſe which can not be but imperfecte. Then is hée forced in the doubtfull ſtormes of Diſpaire, to caſte anker in the quiet hauen of Hope,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:9019:5"/>
then is he taught by the rigour of the law, to clayme the priuiledge of faith, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his owne merites, to the mercies of Almighty God, truſting not in earthly fancies, but in the true fauoure of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly redemption. And this is the fayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bringeth humble feare, &amp; giues increaſe of heauenly wiſdome, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence as it were from a goodly fountaine of grace, all other vertues haue their beginning, but not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaſon alone, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Philoſophers opinion, which appoint Vertue to be ſuch a perfect quality of the mind, that guideth vs directly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of right, towards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> atteining to felicitie, a thing impoſſible vnto vs to deſerue, which by the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nature, and frailtie of fleſh, are commonly withdrawen from that which is good, and contrarywiſe allured to that whiche is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and vncomely. And lyke as the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall plants without grafting, yéelde bitter fruites, and the grounde, that is not by the continuall laboures of Huſbandmen tilled and manured, bringeth forthe drye Moſſe, &amp; vnfruitefull wéedes: none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:9019:6"/>
the deſires and affections of man, not grounded on Humilitie by the feare of God, followe the luſtes of the fleſh, and proude temptations of Satan, whoſe falſe delightes at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth will preſſe them downe into the déepe pitte of perdition: theſe bée the daungers leaſt miſdoubted in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures of youth, whiche in theſe dayes accompt it an aduantage to be famous in vice, and a baſe mind or cowardly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to liue by the ſtricte courſe and directe rule of vertues, whereof héereafter wée ſhall diſcourſe more at large. But nowe muſt we talke of Humilitie, whiche is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the Lanterne of lighte, that guydeth our féete into the way of peace, the ſtarre that leadeth vs to the houſe of true nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the firſt ſteppe of duties, that ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth oure mindes to the worthy déedes of vertue. We ſée the loftie flying Eagle, (whoſe large wings are vnable to exalte the weight of hir body from ground) firſte humbleth hirſelfe wyth lowly ſtoupes, whereby ſhe recouereth greater ſtrength to mount aloft into the Peripheries of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9019:6"/>
Ayre: ſo muſt the mind of him, that ſéekes to haue the full reward of Vertue, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente humbly to fulfill the charge of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and by degrées, to climbe the ſtately ſteppes of aduancement. There bée ſome that blindly iudge the giftes of Fortune (as vayne pompe, and fonde pleaſures of this world) to be the ſoueraigne goodneſſe, and chiefe ſupport of felicitie, in ſo muche as this man carefully ſpendes the whole courſe of his life for encreaſe of wealthe: another languiſhing in fonde deſires, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes by ſundrye diſeaſes empayreth his owne health: And ſome are dayly pampred with delicate meates, and drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the wanton Seas of worldly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And is he therefore happie that is riche? no, for wealth is ſubiecte vnto for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. But is he well pleaſed that hathe pleaſure ſeldome? for commonly ſwéete meate hathe ſower ſauſe, and pleaſaunte mirth is accompanyed with the trayne of lothſome ſorrowes. And doth he bath in bliſſe that luſteth in vnlawfull deſires? or rather offereth himſelfe for a ſacrifice, to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9019:7"/>
be conſumed in Hell fires? then Fortune maketh rich and poore, and Nature giueth health and ſickneſſe, beautie and deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: but héerein conſiſteth no felicitie: for neyther is he to be accompted riche that is neuer ſatiſfyed, nor happie, whoſe ſtedfaſt mind in quiet poſſeſſion of Vertues is not eſtabliſhed.<note place="margin">Summum bonum.</note> A moſt quiet and peaceable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate is felicitie, flowing with abundance of pleaſures, frée from bondage, voyde of feare, &amp; ſubiect to no maner of miſfortune, and ſooner ſhall glad pouertie with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented mind enioy the benefite of ſuch hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly treaſure, than all wordly pompe, &amp; riotous delight, whiche by no meanes can inſinuate themſelues to ſoiourne in the houſe of happie ſtate and tranquilitie: for this cauſe, the valleys are commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly more fruteful than the Mountaines, by reaſon, that lying lowe, and ſhrowded from the ſcorching heate of the Sunne, they receiue more plentifully the droppes of deaw, and naturall fatneſſe, that falleth downe from the tops of the Mountaines. But there be found ſundry branches of humilitie, which ſpred themſelues abrode as it were in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9019:7"/>
of the trée that generally conteineth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all. And firſt receiuing chiefe ſap from the roote of humilitie, ſpringeth out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true knowledge of duties,<note place="margin">Obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia</note> than the which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more commendable in youth, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more profitable in a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth, &amp; nothing more acceptable vnto God, which thing <hi>M. Cicero,</hi> the floure of eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, full wiſely conſidered, when hée wrote thoſe large inſtructions of Duties, wherin ther is no ſorts of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> behalfe, he hath not ſatiſfyed, for ther is the dutie towards our pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; the loue towardes their children liuely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed: the charge of Princes, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of ſubiects: the feare of Magiſtrates, and the execution of lawes; and that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth all in one, the moſt loyal loue, and dutiful regard of our Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of vs all, is there likewiſe moſt manifeſtly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned. But we must rather holde with the doctrine of true Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, that the feare of God, and true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the diuine maieſtie, conteineth all other duties, whiche ſpring from thence, as from the Fountayne of Life, as is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9019:8"/>
aforeſayde. For if all power commeth from God, and authoritie from aboue, no doubt, the Maieſtie of a Prince is with al duties of humilitie to be honoured, and the authoritie of a Magiſtrate by no meanes to be reſiſted. We ought not in minde to conceyue an euill thought, or ſiniſter opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of our Prince and gouernour, muche leſſe then Giantlike to rebell, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to make warres with the Gods: but we ſhould be like children affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Parentes, accompting theyr imperfections our plague, their ſinne, oure ſhame, and their fall our vtter confuſion: for as that member is nothing profitable, but rather hurtfull to the body, whiche by corruption, is lame and vnperfect, ſo that ſubiecte, whoſe minde is drawen into ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye practiſes of diſcord, working the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet of a common peace and tranquility, may iuſtly be cutte off, as an vnprofitable part, or cancker of a common wealth: but whence commeth ſuche vnnaturall affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the child to wiſh the deſtruction of his pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? wherof riſeth ſuch furious rage
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9019:8"/>
in the ſubiect, to rebell againſt his Prince? &amp; what moueth ſuch deſperat madneſſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to betray his own natiue Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey? co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth it not of Pride, couetouſnes, or enuie? and what are theſe cruel tygres, or deſpitefull mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſters, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo vexe the minds of vnhappie men? or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce haue ſuch cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vices their beginning? ſurely from na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture partly, which enclineth to the worſt, nouriſhed by falſe emulation, &amp; confirmed with euill cuſtome, for as <hi>Vergill</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Alitur vitium creſcit<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tegendo, <hi>Vice is nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, and encreaſeth by cloaking.</hi>
                  </hi> Wée muſt therefore withſtand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginnings of ſuch miſchiefs, leaſt peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture lingring delayes bring vntimely repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. For ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gréene wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d healed, and perfectly cloſed vp by the Surgeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an old griefe (which by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is feſtered in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body) can be ſoundly cured: ſo ſhal the tender ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities of youth, by good gouernemente &amp; wholeſome inſtructions, bée ſooner trained to the perfection of vertue, than the mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert affections, and obſtinate deſires of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per yeares, from the lewd practice of vice,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9019:9"/>
he reſtreyned according to the Prouerbe, <hi>That is bredde by the bone, will neuer out the fleſh.</hi> And ſurely, the most neceſſarie practiſe of good education, is with manye other moſt profitable commodities of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, at this time too lightly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded. And is it not a ſcornefull thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a man ſhould teach his Horſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manedge &amp; carere, or his hanke to fetch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lofty turnes abouehead, or hound to follow the ſuite of a ſtriken Déere, and leaue his child in the floure of youth, eyther ſubiect to miſchiefs for want of good gouernement, or that is worſe, waſted in the felowſhip of ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifies, as happily ſhall encourage hym for want of better grace &amp; maintenance, to ſéeke his owne fathers deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſideration of this, &amp; the worthy bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites of learning, I leaue to their priuate iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which know the manifeſt diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of good &amp; euil. And returning to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I ſay, that obedience as in all ages &amp; eſtates it is neceſſary, ſo in youth it ought chiefly to be pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, &amp; principally grafted. Next vnto this ariſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch of patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,<note place="margin">Pacientia.</note> wherin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe trial of wiſdome.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9019:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And a ſtoute vertue is this, that vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the ſwelling rage of wrath, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the inuincible force of nature.<note place="margin">Bias.</note> 
                  <hi>Bias</hi> the wiſe man, being demanded what man was to be thought moſt infortunate, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, euen he that is moſt impatient, adding there vnto this reaſon, that not the loſſe of goodes, or change of fortune, could ſo much proſtrate a mans life, as the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet acceptance of ſuch vnhappie chance doth moleſt, and greeuouſly diſturbe the tranquilitie of the mind: the preſent reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die for ſuch unco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable miſchiefs is only patience, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ouerwhelmeth heapes of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, with hope of ſucceding pleaſure, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſuſteineth the profits of peace and bitter ſtormes of war: patience is the ſhield of intollerable wrongs, that lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the burthen of aduerſitie, &amp; ſeaſoneth the ioyes of proſperitie, the comfortable medicine of ſickneſſe, &amp; the moſt wholſome preſeruatiue of health. What cauſed the Philoſopher <hi>Socrates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Socrates.</note> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of meane birth, to be pronounced the only wiſe man of the whole world, by the deuine Oracles of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:9019:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
but patience? what rayſed the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy renoume of Q. <hi>Griſeld,</hi> whoſe fame is regiſtred in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court of euerlaſting memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? finally, what ſtormes of ſtrife, what cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of fortune, or what force of miſchiefe doth not the ſame patience o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome? for this cauſe wer the ſage Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers wont to be receiued, &amp; highly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéemed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Courts of Princes, that by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> example of their modeſty, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noble Péeres, &amp; rulers of the land, might be the better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed of indifference in the execution of iuſtice, for according to the opinion of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ariſtotl.</note> vnworthily to him is the charge of authoritie committed, that is vnable to reſtreyne &amp; gouerne his owne priuate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. Then if patience in a Prince be comely, and in a Magiſtrate alſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, howe muche more ought it of all good ſubiects dutifully to be embraced: for as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of a Prince is the chiefeſt authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the magiſtrate, ſo are the good condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of rulers the beſt ſtay, and ſtrongeſt defence of inferioures. And thus muche I woulde wiſhe to be generally perſwaded
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:9019:10"/>
vnto youth, that as patience is the porter of prefermente, ſo that all wrathfull and raſhe reuenge, is the ringleader of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, and authoure of deſtruction. But héere ſome will ſay perhappes, what doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is thys, that ſo confoundeth hygh courage? what a cowardly minde hathe he that ſo debaceth manhoode? can it ſtand with the courage of <hi>Achilles</hi> to forbeare? or with the maieſtie of <hi>Caeſar</hi> to take wrong? yea Sir, and (by youre leaue be it ſpoken) howe muche the more noble is the minde, ſo muche leſſe is the reuenge of priuate wrongs by hymſelfe eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and for thys cauſe, that if the wrong conſiſt in words, be miſdoubteth not his good fame and credite ſufficiente to diſproue and confounde the weake ſtrength of falſe reportes: but if pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked wyth vniuſt déedes, to ſéeke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge of iniuries. It appeaſeth the wrath of a noble conqueroure, more to bée able to puniſhe, than it contenteth hym vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlye to deſtroy. Was it agaynſte the courage of <hi>Hercules,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hercules</note> that hée reſtored
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9019:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Priamus</hi> vnto the Sceptre and poſſeſſions of his father <hi>Laomedon?</hi> was it againſte the honour of King <hi>Hidaſpis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hidaſpis.</note> that he par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſe traytor <hi>Oroondates?</hi> &amp; was it againſte the maieſtie &amp; manhoode of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der,</hi> that he refuſed the vnequall cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge of Quéene <hi>Thomyris?</hi> no, but rather a ſpeciall ſigne of heroicall magnamitie, to deſpiſe light wrongs. and nothing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard ſuch meane aduentures, wherevnto this Prouerb may be applyed, <hi>Aquila non capit muſcas, <hi>the loftie fierce Eagle prayes not on ſillie Flyes.</hi>
                  </hi> But I meane not here to praiſe <hi>Therſites</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Aiax,</hi> nor <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iax</hi> is to be preferred before <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> for it is not ynough for a man to be bolde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out witte, nor ſtrong withoute wiſdome, but vnto whome thoſe vertues are indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently graunted, he hathe in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente an abſolute force and perfection of manhode. Again, there be diuers kinds of ſufferance,<note place="margin">Fortitudo</note> for as the execution of iuſtice, and wrongfull perſecution, are not equal, ſo conſtreyned ſufferance, and humble pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, are not alike. The patience of good
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9019:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Caliſthenes</hi> the Philoſopher, enduring the cruell tormentes deuiſed by the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of <hi>Alexander,</hi> was wonderfull: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſperate boldneſſe, or rather obſtinate ſtubberneſſe of Quéene <hi>Olimpias</hi> at hir death, was not alike, nor by anye meanes commendable. Thus we ſée that patience is the armour of righteouſneſſe, agaynſte whiche not the bitter ſtormes of aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, not the furious rage of tirannie, no not the cruell paſſions of death it ſelfe can take place, or any thing preuayle.<note place="margin">Comitas.</note> The laſt branche of Humilitie, outwardly ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the fruites of vertues, humbleth it ſelfe in the face of all men, and beares the floures of courteſie. And truth it is, that ſuche as is the trée, like is the fruite, for neyther ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we gather Figges of thornes, nor Grapes of thiſtles. This Vertue, as in all places, amongſt all ſortes it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, ſo in the Pallace of a Prince, (which is the Nurſſe of Fame, and The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atre of Vertues) it ought chiefely to bée foſtered, and dayly practiſed. So agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the nature of mankinde is thys
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9019:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
gentle affection, that by the conſente of ſage men, it hathe bin called Humanitie, and ſince by the friendlye corruption of the common ſorte (as I geſſe) from the Courte, it nowe taketh the name of courteſie: but wée wyll not ſtande ſo muche vppon the name, as the perfecte vſe héereof, although in déede of late, amongſt oure Engliſhe Poets, hathe riſen a doubtefull controuerſie, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng the true chriſtening of thys Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, in ſo muche, as ſome call it a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarde courteſie, or in playne tearmes, diſſemblyng flatterie, that couertly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth poſſeſſion of mens myndes, in the Courtes of Princes nowe adayes: but as theſe haue theyr priuiledge to ſpeake what they liſte, ſo I doubte not, but manye of the other haue a protection of ſelfe wyll, to doe what they lyke beſt.</p>
               <p>Theſe menne maye bée reſembled to the Philoſopher <hi>Antiſthenes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Antist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henes.</note> who walked on a tyme in the common place at <hi>Athens</hi> amongſt the Nobilitie, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9019:12"/>
muche dyſguiſed in apparell, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Ragges in ſtedde of Robes, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng thereby couertlye, to ſteale the name of Humilitie, for that hée was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe of good abilitie, and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wellknowen.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Socrates,</hi> ſo ſoone as hée pecey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued hym in that place thus attyred, cryed aloude, Beholde, a man maye ſée the ſecrete ambition of <hi>Antiſthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> euen through the holes of his cloke, whome preſentlye the people all behelde with ſcornefull deriſion. And thus was the déepe diſſimulation of <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> diſcouered, by the readie witte, and ſharp rebuke of <hi>Socrates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I fynde in an olde writer a moſte vertuous example of Humilitie, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by the Kyng of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> whyche on a time ryding in hys Chariot, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed wyth a troupe of hys No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, preparing themſelues to ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye diſportes, and martiall feates of exerciſe, glanced his eyes aſide by chance,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9019:13"/>
and beheld a couple of auncient poore men that were trauelling on the way, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon he commaunded his Chariot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to bée ſtayed, and comming downe from thence, marched alone to méete theſe two Pilgrimes, whome he chéerefully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, and humbly on his knées embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and after muche familiar talke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene them had, the King ſente them forwarde on their iourney, very richly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, himſelfe returning to his chariot as ioyfull as if he had done ſome greate aduenture. But this thing done by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King openly in the face of all the nobilitie, and chief royaltie of the Court, was amongſt ſuche a multitude, one cauſe of diuers ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, &amp; the only occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſundry offences, in ſo muche, as ſome maruelling at thys ſtrange curteſie, with admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie much aſtoniſhed. Other murmuring, grudged at the gifts ſo vaynely beſtowed, but chiefely, the prouder ſort of the nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, were gréeuouſly vexed with ſcornefull diſdeyne, at the facte, amongſt whome, the Kings brother was one, whiche preſently
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9019:13"/>
vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming home to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Court, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewe him ſelfe cloſely into the Kinges chamber, where finding him with opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie of tyme, ſayde theſe wordes: Syr, I let you vnderſtande, that the Lords and chiefe royaltie of the Court, wonderfully miſlyked the ſtraunge enterteinment you gaue to the baſe beggers by the way, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting it rather to the plaine diſgrace and prophaning of your royall Maieſtie, than to the vaine pretence of any better ende, and thus much is ſpoken in ſecrete of me, by nature your brother, and by dueties your humble ſubiect. The Kyng hearing theſe words, gaue him hartie thankes for his labour, diſſembling his purpoſe vntill the euening when all the Lords were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to their lodgings. Then commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he the deadly trompe to be ſounded at his brothers gate, which by cuſtome of that countrey was wont to gyue war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning preſently before the death of a Péere vpon iudgement not to be reuerſed. The ſounde whereof ſtrooke ſuch a terrour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him and his whole familie, that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9019:14"/>
his friendes togither, they lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly mourning, paſſed all the night, looking for nothing but death: And the morning was nowe come, when with a ſorowfull traine of mourners himſelf the kings bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther clothed in ſackcloth, bare heade with his comely lockes negligently diſperſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, gaſtly to behold, with his eyes fixed vnto death, came thus into the Court, aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hall humbly on his knées at the kings mercie: wherof y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king being aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, came downe at length vnto his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, bearing him ſelf ignorant of this tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical ſhewe, wherof notwithſtanding, he him ſelf had bin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chief author, &amp; chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demaunded before them all, what was the cauſe of ſo ſtraunge an alteration in his brother, which heauily tolde him the ſounde of the trumpe had thus fearefully warned him to put him ſelfe at the féete of his maieſties fauour: wherat y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king ſmy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſayd. And is this the cauſe of ſo great a terrour vnto thée, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hither vnto vs thou art come ſo diſguiſed? can the feare of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9019:14"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eath by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of man which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertaine, ſo ſoone co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thy lofty corage? But why didſt thou then ſo ſkornefullye wonder at me, which humbled my ſelf ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday when I beheld the liuely and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe image of death (whoſe force no man can eſcape) in thoſe auncient men whome for age I courteouſly ſalute? was it not more fearfull to behold the figure of death than to heare the ſound of a trumpe? is it not leſſe cauſe of wonder in me to obey the lawes of God and nature, than in thée to feare the iudgement of man, whiche is frayle? Therefore I pardon, and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe thée my brother, that as thou haſte bene ouer dreadfull of man heretofore, ſo that thou reuerently feare God aboue all men hereafter. With theſe and ſuche lyke wordes, the good Kyng modeſtlye reprooued and friendlye chaſtiſed the proude ſurquedrye of hys owne brother, to the better example of all the Nobilitie of his Court. A worthy mirrour of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maieſty of a Prince, &amp; an eſpecial
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9019:15"/>
paterne of the rare clemencie and curteſie of a Kyng. And thus we ſée the ſtate of Princes muche better by dignitie of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues mainteyned, than by the force of worldly pompe and riches ſtrengthened and vphelde, the fame of true nobilitie by gentleneſſe &amp; curteſie foſtered, the wealth of ſubiectes by duetifull obedience increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and to conclude, the towarde wittes and ſingular good capacities of younge Courteours by ſufferaunce well furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and through modeſt behauiour &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, worthily to be aduaunced.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Company and fellovvship.</head>
               <head>CHAP. 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ythagoras was wont to ſay, that commonly in a multitude the number of the wicked is moſt, &amp; the flocke of good men leaſte. How true the opinion of this Philoſopher is, by dayly experience it is too plainlye prooued: For where there is one man in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9019:15"/>
theſe dayes incouraged by the rewarde of vertue, to ſearch out the ſecretes of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, there be many times as many which no doubt allured by the ſmiling lookes of vanitie, doe ſpend their whole time in the contemplation and practice of folly. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of commeth ſlouth the onely nurſe of néed, pryde, the chiefe authour of penury, &amp; fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy luſt, the mother of all miſchiefes. And to be ſhort, what ſhame, what ſorrowe, griefe, ſickneſſe, plague, death, and that is worſe than death, what ſeuile bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage doeth not this deceiptfull emulation and peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t force of ill company procure. But there is a more curious kinde of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſprong vp of late dayes amongeſt vs, which are ſo farre from imitating of any man, that they principally ſtudy to make them ſelues lyke vnto no man. And by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Court there be multitudes, and many men muſt néedes be diuerſly diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, it behoueth a young Courtiour at his entrance, principally to be aduiſed in the choyce of his fellowſhip and company, for ſurely it is the chiefe point &amp; firſt meanes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9019:16"/>
to winne or looſe creadite and eſtimation: Let him remember the good Counſayle of the kyngly Prophete <hi>Dauid,</hi> that ſaeith, <hi>with the iuſt thou ſhalt bee made righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal.</note> 
                  <hi>but with the froward thou ſhalt learne frowardneſſe.</hi> There be ſome, and I feare too many, that knowe not what goodneſſe meanes, neyther will they come where honeſtie dwelleth, vnthriftineſſe is theyr hauntyng houſe, vncleanneſſe theyr de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, quarrellyng is their exerciſe, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne their companion, and ſwearyng their common talke: So that a young Gentleman accompanyed wyth ſuche companyons, ſhall ſoone with the ſpoyle of hys goodes be diſcharged of the waight of hys creadite, for if hée haue ought, they will wayt of purpoſe to make hym ſpende, they will ſpare theyr owne to be liberall of hys, vntyll all be gone, then flyng about for a newe ſupplie by ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother companyon, which is a foule ſhift and a ſhamefull refuge: By this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes manye a towarde youth is vndone, his preferment farre of, and here by his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9019:16"/>
folly hath a very good furtheraunce. For ſuche as they are, ſuche ſhall hée be, both for conuerſation of lyfe and eſtimation. To auoyde ſuche miſchiefe therefore, I woulde counſayle him at the firſt to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the company of ſuche as are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and wyſe, to ſéeke the felowſhyp of thoſe that are learned, and ſo by litle and little to inſinuate hym ſelfe into the countenaunce of the beſt, whoſe eſtate is ſtedfaſtlye grounded on the rocke of Princely fauour, neyther muſt he blunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye at the firſt be roundyng with olde Courteours, whiche wyll not raſhelye admytte younge babes into theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes, but content hym ſelfe wyth the companye of the inferiours, whoſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhyp is commendable. Some are of greater experience by reaſon of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall affayres, other haue traueyled to learne the languages and manners of ſtraunge countreys, ſome at home doe ſtudie pleaſaunt hyſtoryes, and haue a goodlye gyfte of eloquence, and other by byrth are not onelye Noble, but in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9019:17"/>
conuerſation of lyfe, and countenance ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry comely, with ſuch men ought he firſt to acquainte him ſelfe: for theſe and ſuche lyke excelling the common ſort, are beſt worthy to be eſtéemed, not that the reſt of meaner wittes ſhould be reiected, but that the beſt ought chiefly to be folowed. And as one Swallow brings not in ſommer as it is in the prouerbe, ſo the ſtrength of one onely vertue, is not ſufficient to knytte the ſtedfaſt knot of true friendſhyp, nor one good condition inough to ſeale the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect bandes of amitie, but the lykenes of mindes, and ſimilitudes of maners, for the moſt part maketh true friendes: but to what ende is this? ſhall we make a friende of euery ſlight companion? No ſir, but herein is the difference expreſſed betwéene ſocietie and friendſhip, namely that this requireth preſent ſhewes of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie but the other by longer tract of tyme is grounded, and by chaunge of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune beſt tryed and made manifeſt. And in choice of felowſhip, he that féedes his eyes with outward ſhows of brauery, more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:9019:17"/>
his mynd is fixed in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templation of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward beautie, may chaunce (while others clime y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſteps of worthye Fame) ſo ſhrewd himſelf in the darke ſhadowes of reproch: for <hi>Al is not golde that glyſters,</hi> but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vnder the lookes of loue, lurketh the cruel plague of deſpight, &amp; vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> floures of ſwéete fauour, lyes hidde the Serpent of deadly diſpleaſure: <hi>In truſt is treaſon,</hi> and to conclude, in felowſhip oftimes is found moſte wicked and deceitefull falſeſhood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Talke and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.</head>
               <head>CHAP. 3.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Peach is a comfortable gift, amongſt all other creatures graunted by the prouidence of God only vnto mankind, whereby we are taught to vnderſtande the meaning of good and euil. For the tong is an interpreter of the mind, and according to the opinion of ſome Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9019:18"/>
it is the greateſt difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs and vnreaſonable creatures, that we excel them in talke and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. <hi>Socrates</hi> had a child of noble birth brought vnto him, by gentle inſtruction to be imboldned, for he was of nature baſhful vnto whom ſayde <hi>Socrates</hi> euen at his firſt comming, ſpeake child, that I may know thée, meaning that ſpeache diſcouereth the good or ill conditions of the minde: But if <hi>Socrates</hi> himſelf were aliue in theſe dayes, he might perhaps by that plains principle be very cunningly deceyued: for why? the times alas are chaunged, and with the times the maners of men are altered, their hartes are hardened with vntruth, theyr affections grounded on falſeſhood, and their ſmoth tongs are filed with ſwéete phraſes of diſſembling flatterie. Where is that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be founde whoſe wordes and déedes are indifferent? where doeth he liue, whoſe friendſhip is faithful? nay rather who liues that doeth not learne to be diſloyall? and what is the cauſe of ſuch and ſo great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes? ſure the abuſe and vile diſordering
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:9019:18"/>
of ſundry good giftes of God. Let vs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for example, that eſpeciall gift &amp; ſwéete abounding knowledge of eloquence, which hath bene heretofore, by the learned tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the reconciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of princes, and true eſtabliſhing of peace, worthyly employed: and nowe it is in the brewing of diſcorde, and mouing of hateful warres, moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly practiſed. It hath bene heretofore in deuiſing holeſome Lawes, for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of a common wealth ſeriouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, and now it is in defeſaunce of right too commonlye ſet abroche. It hath bene heretofore in the praiſe of vertues exerciſe plentifully beſtowed, and now it is in the maintenaunce of vice and cunning en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticementes of follie (I loth to ſpeake) to ſhamefullye, ſcornefullye, and too licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly abuſed.</p>
               <p>What, feare to ſpeake truely? what li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertye to lye falſely? what ſhame to talke wyſelye? what prayſe to ſpeake fondely? what paine to bée plaine? what pleaſure to diſſemble? finallye what ſlouth to commende? and what haſte
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9019:19"/>
and diligence to ſlaunder, is now commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſed amongſt men? y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euen to liue is nothing elſe but to diſſemble. And herein y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecrete prouidence of God is wonderfull, whyche vnto euerye good gifte hath added ſome inconuenience, bicauſe we ſhould not be ſurpriſed with pompe of pride of anye time. We ſée the brighte ſunne beames whiche giueth gladſome lighte ouer all the world, and yet ſcortcheth the gréen graſſe, and is hurtfull ſtill to beholde: likewiſe the ſwéete floure yéeldes honny to the prettye Bée, and giues poyſon to the lothſome ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: none otherwiſe is it with vs, touching neceſſarie vſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tong, which vnto ſome (beyng wel vſed) and diſcretely gouerned, is the cauſe of highe prefermente, and to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers lewdely practiſed, and licentiouſlye abuſed, it is verily the ſharpe inſtrument of miſchiefe. And it were better for a man openly to be hurte with ſwordes, than ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretely to be wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euil words. There be many vertues expreſſed in diſcrete talke and wyſe communication, but amongeſt them al, there is none that commendeth a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9019:19"/>
Courtier, ſo much as the carefull héede he taketh in the praiſe or diſpraiſe of any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for neyther is a friend in the Court haſtily to be commended, nor an open enimye ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretely to be ſlaundered. And as I woulde wiſhe all men buſilye to prayſe none, ſo I woulde haue no man bitterly to backbyte any. It is the duetie of a Magiſtrate to enter into iudgement of manners, and not the part of a priuate ſubiecte, to note anye man with opprobrious words for his euill behauiour, not that vice is not in al places and at all times to be deteſted, but that faultes and offences, by eche man are not to be reproued: for of little medling com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth greate roſte, and of licentious talke oft times enſueth much vnquietneſſe. And ſith the beſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſome thing may deſerue blame, it is moſte requiſite, that one man ſhould bear with anothers imperfections, and rather charitablye to admoniſhe, than maliciouſlye to reproue another mans of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. The next Vertue (that bringeth infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite commodities vnto the well diſpoſed minde) is in concealing of ſecrets, I mean
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9019:20"/>
ſuch counſayles in any reſpect as are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted of truſt vnto any man. It is good to forbeare to talke of things néedeleſſe to be ſpoken, but it is muche better to conceale things daungerous to be tolde. And tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince eſpecially with the Péeres and principall rulers, it ſtandeth muche vppon to be ſilent: And of all other things impertinent vnto us, it behoueth not to be curious and inquiſitiue. For it is an olde prouerb <hi>Quae ſupra nos nihil ad nos.</hi> Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer if a man be called to the table of hys betters, where occaſion maye be giuen to ſpeake, in anye wiſe he muſte be well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed what and wherof is the queſtion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he entend to make aunſwere, neyther muſte he be to long in diſcourſe, leaſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes they ſhould ſaye that he loues well to heare himſelfe talke, nor to curious in reaſoning of the truth, nor to bolde in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of an argument, leaſt he be noted of impudence and want of diſcreation: but in thoſe pointes chiefely, muſte he labour to delight by good order, obſeruing <hi>Decorum</hi> in theſe and al other his ſaying: And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:9019:20"/>
he muſte take héede not to muche to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtome his tongue vnto one phraſe, nor dwell in any one knide of diſcourſe, leaſte for want of better Muſicke, he proue an in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrument of mirth to the ſcornefull. And yet in this pointe manye cunning Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours beguyle themſelues nowe and then, except they take the figure <hi>Tautologia,</hi> for a comely grace, which the <hi>Rethoricia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> were wonte to condemne for a vice: And now commes <hi>Thraſo</hi> vaunting himſelf of his owne déedes of armes, and high points of ſeruice, nexte vnto him <hi>Therſites</hi> the minion powreth out his doubtfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemes, and with amorous diſcourſes wéeneth to be able to inſinuate himſelfe into the fauoure of the Goddeſſes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: And other there be, whom no ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous cauſe or waightie matter can remoue from luring of their haukes, rayning their horſe, or folowing their hounds: But theſe &amp; ſuch like, peraduenture are wel furniſhed with the giftes of fortune, for good cauſe, to ſupplye the want of diſcretion. Laſtly, touching the occaſion and order of talke,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9019:21"/>
it behoueth him much, that is conuerſant amongſt the higheſt, to giue them leaue to chooſe their owne matter, and (except it be in a caſe preiudiciall to none) to let them be content with their owne opinion, only for duetie ſake, afording ſome few words of courſe for common aunſwere: neyther muſt be ſhewe himſelfe ouer manifeſtly to miſlike the maſter, leaſt that ſhould proue a greater offence, than ſomewhat to diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And if in diſcourſe of talke it hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned any cholerick words to paſſe (as there is none ſo modeſt, that can alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine his affections) it is good to lappe vp the matter in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end, with a curteous fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well at the parting, and to giue a gentle conge at the next meeting, leaſt peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſome malice might therof ariſe, which thou muſt at all times ſéeke to auoyde and eſchewe like vnto poyſon. And he that can thus ſtay his tong, and moderate his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, hath a very good furtheraunce, no doubt, to aduance his eſtate, or at the leaſt to paſſe his time without troubles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:9019:21"/>
               <head>Of Modeſt behauior.</head>
               <head>CHAP. 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath béene a doubtfull que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of long time amongſt the learned, touchyng the firſte cauſe and originall occaſion of Gentrie. In ſo muche as the Poets haue painfully trauelled heretofore,<note place="margin">Poetae.</note> by fond authoritie of fayned fables, &amp; vaine proofe of falſe arguments, to perſuade the true coniunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heauenly bodies with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corporall ſubſtance of mankind, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by concluding Gentrie to be the verye ofſpring of the Goddes. Nor far diſſenting from theſe menne was the opinion of thoſe Ethnike Philoſophers,<note place="margin">Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phi.</note> which would haue their nobilitie to deriue their pedigrées fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sunne, from the Moone, and manye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther celeſtiall creatures, the rather to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their high courage and magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. But theſe vayne ſanſies of Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme are already by the lighte of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell and true Doctrine of Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:9019:22"/>
ſufficiently drowned. There reſteth yet, the groſſe erroure of the common ſorte of people to be refuted, whoſe churliſhe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion hathe ſuppoſed onely riches to haue bin the beginning of noble birth and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, for (ſaye they) <hi>when Adam dolue, and Eue did spin, then was there no ſuch Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle kinne:</hi> and true it is, but yet nothing to the purpoſe. For as the goodly frame and beautifull ſtage of the whole worlde was not in a moment raiſed all at once, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ineſtimable wiſedome of God, broughte by degrées to ſuche a wonderfull perfection, &amp; moſte ſtéedfaſt continuance. So the ſéede of man from age to age, did encreaſe into multitudes, diuiding themſelues into ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie ſocieties, and by diuine prouidence, at laſte taught to finde out and practize the neceſſarie helpe of ciuil gouernment. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of commeth the crown of Princely digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: hereof riſeth the banner of true nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie: and from hence are blazed the aunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent armes of Gentrie. But (ſaye they) ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches was the cauſe of their promotions:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9019:22"/>
Wealth was the occaſion of ſuch worthie calling, and by the waighte of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, it is likely their eſtate was peazed in the ballance of Eſtimation. And is it likely indéede, that the cauſe ſhould be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte of ſuche an abſolute perfection? but that is contrary to natural reaſon, for ſuch as is the cauſe, like is the effect: or is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that ſuche fauourable helpe of diuine wiſedome, whych was theyr guyde in eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing that kinde of gouernement, ſhould then faile them in the appointing of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities? but it is more probable, that the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall affections of the mind by fréee choice, would rather admitte the worthy diſpoſed and vertuous men to take the ſupremacie and firſt charge of gouernment. And thus muche reaſon prouoketh me to beléeue. But to returne to the purpoſe: If the worthy fame of Vertues alone, hathe rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed inferiors vppe to the toppe and type of Honour: if by valiaunt déeds of armes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie hathe béene aduaunced: if vppon ſuche foundation of manners Gentrie
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:9019:23"/>
was firſt grounded, howe muche more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie is it nowe and euermore, that ſo comely vertues of all men, and eſpeciallye of Gentlemen ſhoulde bée embraced? for wilt thou be beloued of all men? then thou muſte be curteous and deſpiſe none: wilte thou be praiſed? vſe good conditions: wilte thou be honored of the people? then be loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to thy Prince and Countrey: and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wilt thou be dutifully obeyed of others? then thou muſte humbly feare God thy ſelfe. There be many kindes of Vertues which the wiſemen haue called Moral and Intellectuall, whereof ſome be common, both to the affections of the minde, and the outwarde exerciſe of the bodye, ſuche is truth, manhoode, right, modeſtie in behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, curteſie in ſpeache, ſobrietie, bountie, chaſte life, true friendſhippe, and ſuche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but the reſte, as cunning, knowlege, prudence, patience, &amp; wiſedome, are ſubiect only to inward contemplation, &amp; therfore more heroical and diuine. And theſe are the true ſéedes, ſettes and ſciences, whiche in youth ought ſpéedily to be ſowen, ſoundlye
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:9019:23"/>
planted, and moſte artificially grafted.</p>
               <p>The Romanes (whoſe eſtate for poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike gouernment, far ſurmounted al other dominions of the worlde) hadde ſuche care for the trayning vp of youth in vertue and good manners, that they made lawes, and ordayned a ſpeciall Magiſtrate, to foreſée that none ſhoulde liue ydle. And amongeſt all other Vertues, equitie and trueth was there of ſuche eſtimation, that they mighte by no meanes beare rule whiche were ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of couetouſneſſe, nor hardly be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to inherite, whiche in their youth had bin knowen to haue been common lyers. In ſo muche as the Emperoure <hi>Traianus</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he hadde ſlaine King <hi>Cebalus</hi> the father in battaile, and taken his yong ſon to be kepte priſoner, during his nonage in the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> with much add graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his life, and due ſucceſſion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vnto him, onely vpon this condition, that he ſhoulde be diligently taught, &amp; well inſtructed in Vertues, and for this cauſe appointed his gouernor &amp; him to continue ſtil within the precincts of his Court. But
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:9019:24"/>
the yong Prince hauing libertie to ſolace himſelfe with ſome of his companions, on a time brake into the Emperors Orchard, where they buſily applyed themſelues in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> choice of ſwéete fruits to ſatiſfie their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh delight, whom the Emperor himſelf by chance out of windowe perceiued in that place, nor much diſcontent therewyth, hée came downe alone, &amp; met the Prince with his companions, meaning to haue appoſed him in ſundry points of his ſchollerſhippe, and aſked firſt from whence hée came, vnto whom the young Prince aunſwered, from ſchoole, and ſtoutely maintained the ſame to his face: whiche proude faulte and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent boldeneſſe in the childe, ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully moued the wrath, and kindled the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of the Emperor towards him, that he would (notwithſtanding his former par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don) haue diſpatched him both from life and liuing when hée came to riper yeares, had it not bin for the ſecond ſuite and great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of the Nobilitie, whiche earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded him to the contrary. Suche was the ſeueritie of thys Emperor <hi>Traia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:9019:24"/>
in chaſtiſing of falſhood, &amp; the worthie fame of all the Romanes in the maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Truth. And ſurely, if ſuche lawes were executed in theſe daies, we ſhold nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue the cities gréeuouſly vexed wyth corrupt Magiſtrates, nor the quiet ſtréets troubled with ſo many franticke frayes of brawling vnthrifts. But where ſhoulde a man ſéeke Iuſtice, but of Magiſtrates? where ſhould he find peace, if not in cities? &amp; of whome ſhould we learne good maners, but of Courteors? For in ſuch a multitude &amp; dayly méeting of the moſte noble, wiſe, &amp; valiant perſons, the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry gifts of nature &amp; goodly vertues are ſo bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully beſtowed, no otherwiſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a beautiful garden, the ſundrie ſwéet flowers, which in the Spring time make a pleaſant ſhew in ſight, &amp; yéeld a moſt delicate ſauour of delight. In thys place (as in a ſtrong bulwark of defence) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worthy Knights returning fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dreadfull warres, refreſh their weary limmes wyth comfortable, words and greate entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: here the wiſe conſulte as in a moſte quiet Senate houſe, touching the welfare and commodities of a common wealth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:9019:25"/>And likewiſe here the flower of Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie dayly practiſe déedes of armes, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe all feates of Chiualrie moſte néedful in the defence of their Prince and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: and howe muche thoſe men are to bée blamed, whiche (in ſteade of ſuche good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe) vſe onely the practiſe of moſte laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious paſtimes, it appeareth by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> whiche in regarde of hys ſwéete wife at home, famed himſelfe to bée diſtraught with ſoddaine furies, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent he mighte withdrawe himſelfe from the ſiege of <hi>Troy.</hi> For when he hadde béen thereof aduertized by <hi>Nauplus,</hi> and other worthy Captaines of the Gréekes, he was penſiue all the night, conſulting with hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for ſome fine deuice, or ſuttle ſleighte, to winde himſelfe from the warres: and on the nexte morrowe he furiouſly brake oute into the fieldes, where he founde a plowe, wherein (in ſteade of Oxen) he had yoked other wild beaſts, which he tooke by craft, and thus eared the grounde, whiche after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes he cauſed to be ſowed wyth Baye ſalte. But <hi>Nauplus</hi> vnderſtanding hereof,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:9019:25"/>
ſoone ſmelt his deuice, and cauſed his yong ſonne <hi>Telemachus</hi> to be broughte foorth, &amp; laide in the furrowe, whome, when <hi>Vliſſes</hi> perceiued, ouercome by the ſtrong force of naturall affection, he turned his ploughe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, &amp; ſaued the life of the child, to his own ſhamefull diſcredite. To whome <hi>Nauplus</hi> cried out aloude: Nowe maiſte thou with ſhame leaue off thy diſſembled furie, ſith thy councelles are betrayed, and the deapth of thy deuice is throughlye ſounded: and couldeſt thou (cowarde) for filthy luſte for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worthy enterpriſe of wars: couldeſt thou perſuade thy ſelfe for wanton loue to leaue the honorable déeds of Knighthoode? It is a greate ſhame to a King, to winne the loue of a woman, and léeſe the honoure of the fielde, and therefore I councell thée <hi>Vliſſes</hi> to leaue ſuch lewd practiſes hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, &amp; follow the martiall déeds of arms, moſt fit for thy calling. And thus was <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſes</hi> entrapped in his owne ſnare, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumuented with his own ſhameful deuice. But here might a greate queſtion ariſe in controuerſie, whether are more profitable
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:9019:26"/>
of the valiant or wiſe in the adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the common wealth, which I had rather cloſe vppe with the opinion of <hi>Cicero</hi> that ſaid: <hi>Parui ſunt foris arma niſi est conſilium domi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nexte vnto theſe Vertues appeareth bountiful Magnificence, whoſe beames are ſo bright ſhining in the déeds of Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, that I ſuppoſe to darke cloudes of Couetouſneſſe are not able to Eclipſe the light of ſuch a goodly vertue: And we muſt eſtéeme it a dreame, where men ſaye, that Engliſh hoſpitalitie is fled, or rather Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphoſed into the likeneſſe of Italian thrift, Spaniſh pride, and other outlandiſh Parſimony: which if it be in dreaming fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, but too truely found by common experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, it is a thing moſte lamentable, and eſpecially to be blamed in thoſe which ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo much vpon the termes of honorable an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, and yet in Tauernes, &amp; ſcornefull places kéepe their chiefe hoſpitalitie. If a man ſhould reaſon with theſe men, &amp; aſke what is the thing they chiefly deſire, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they would ſay Fame, Power, or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9019:26"/>
thrée ſpirituall giftes of Grace in déede, but whiche of them liketh you beſte? Doeſt thou thirſt after the ſwéete <hi>Nectar</hi> &amp; Heauenlye perpetuall flowing ſtreames of Fame: but there is no ſuche dulcet liquor to be founde in Tauerns: Vertue is the onelye fountaine from whence theſe riue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets haue their beginning: for this cauſe the diuine Poet <hi>Homer</hi> did record the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy déedes of <hi>Hector</hi> and <hi>Achilles:</hi> this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Virgil</hi> to diſcourſe the painfull trauels of <hi>Aeneas:</hi> and likewiſe the whole compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Hiſtoriographers, haue left the déeds and workes of antiquitie vnto all poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, onely for example of Vertue. But doe you ambitiouſly deſire to beare rule? then you muſte firſte learne to obey, for what duties can ye looke for at the hands of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, whom you diſdain, when you proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſlike the authoritie of ſuperiors from whence commeth youre honoure? Is it Libertie that you ſéek? then can you not be frée till you be able to reſtraine youre af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: For howe can he enioy the commodities of Peace, whiche delighteth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:9019:27"/>
in the practiſe of diſcord? If he be frée that is ſubiecte to feare, or happy that pines in ſorrowes, or quiet that burneth in wrath, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is he at libertie, which overruled by his affections: but it is farre otherwiſe, and therefore in my iudgement, he is frée from libertie, and inferiour to bondage. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if we woulde be crowned with euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fame, if we ſéeke pleaſantly to liue, and honorably to dye, to rule with power, and to be feared with fauour, and laſtely, to be like vnto the Goddes themſelues, we muſte be liberall in reward of dueties, and bountifull in due conſideration of deſerts. The Emperour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was ſo bountiful in rewards toward his ſubiects, that he wold ſuffer no day to paſſe, wherein he had not diuerſly performed ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry déeds of charitie. What a Princely rewarde was giuen to <hi>Virgil</hi> by the noble <hi>Octauia,</hi> the mother of <hi>Marcellus,</hi> for a few lines writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy praiſe of hir ſonne? howe mindful was that highe renowned King <hi>Alexander,</hi> of his friendly gouernors, whiche in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Perſia</hi> commaunded a riche cheſte,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:9019:27"/>
which conteined chiefe parte of the ſpoile, to be reſerued for <hi>Homer.</hi> Theſe were the vertues of the Gréekes and Romanes, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted their names of the Booke of eternall memorie.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, there be comely graces,<note place="margin">Modestia</note> aſwell in geſture as other behauiour, to be noted in a Courteour: and it behoueth him much that daily ſtandeth in the face of his Prince, and chiefe royaltie of the Realme, to be modeſt in his lookes, and verye cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpecte of behauioure. <hi>Heliodorus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heliod.</note> or at leaſte, the friendlye tranſlatour of hys workes, reſembling <hi>Theagines</hi> vnto the valiaunt <hi>Achilles,</hi> both in ſtature and al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther outward comely proportions of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy maketh them equall, but for his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, (whiche diſcloſeth the modeſtie of the minde) he preferred <hi>Theagines</hi> before the other, in that he was more humbly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and farre more courteous of ſpeach, for whiche he gyueth him a ſingular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation. And to ſaye trueth, what is the comelineſſe of perſonage without good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nners? ſurely it may be likened to the Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:9019:28"/>
image, wherin is much arte, &amp; no ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe, moſt curious workmanſhip, &amp; little vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. But in geſture &amp; behauiour there are as many ſhameful vices to be eſchued, as there be comely graces to be followed: for I would not wiſh a yong man to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfet ſuch grauitie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he become a Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latche, nor a double curteſie maker, which is ſcornful, nor a ceremonious cap giuer to al men, for that is ridiculous, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he muſt be neither ſhéepiſh, nor yet paſt ſhame, that will ſéeke to aduance himſelfe to credite by good maners &amp; modeſt behauior. There be ſome whiche loue rather to ſet their lookes in a Glaſſe, than learne to ſit comely in the ſaddle: another ſtalkes in the ſtréets (as we ſay) like one that would ſteale Cranes: ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beares the countenance of a Lion, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps whoſe courage is not worth a Léeke: this wily fellowe ſhewes euerye man hys ſword, which hath bin the death of ſo many frogs in <hi>Ireland:</hi> and other tels the wonders of ſtrange countries, &amp; therein vſeth the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of a Trauailer: and laſtely, ſome are euer exclayming on their ſtepmothers
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:9019:28"/>
fortune, and whine at the ſorrowes of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie. But theſe (in my iudgement) had rather chooſe Follie for their playfellowe and companion, than the haue Vertue their guide &amp; ſafeconduct vnto wiſedome. There is a meane and mediocritie in all thinges, whiche he that can indifferentlye obſerue, hathe attained euen to the full perfection of Vertue.</p>
               <p>It commendeth a Courteour like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to bée generallye ſéene and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced in many thinges, for the knowledge of all thinges is profitable, but the abuſe of anye thing is vncomely. I haue knowen very wiſe men, which traueling by chance in the company of mean Artificers, would not thinke ſcorne to talke, but take delight to diſcourſe with ſuche, euen of the vileſt trades that are to be neceſſarily vſed in a common wealth. Swéete honny is not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of one onelye, flower, nor lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is had out of one booke, nor Wiſedom likewiſe is attayned by the practiſe of one Vertue alone. And wée muſte learne alſo to frame oure ſpeache and behauiour
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:9019:29"/>
according to the place and company, not to talk with Prieſts of loue, nor with Ladies of religion, not to diſcourſe with childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wars, nor with Princes of trifles: neither in a tragicall miſfortune to be too muche daunted with fear, nor in a ſodain felicitie too farre ſurpriſed with delight. And in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſcourſe we muſt remember to inferre duties by deſert, mirth with meaſure, and pleaſure by commodities, for according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Poet, <hi>Omne tulit punctum qui miſcuit vtile dulci.</hi> To conclude, in al our actions &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditions, we muſt prefer the ſteadfaſt coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaile of aduiſed policie, before the raſh en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe of malaperte boldeneſſe. It is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to deſerue euerlaſting fame with noble <hi>Fabius</hi> which ſaued his country by delays, than to periſhe with ſhamefull <hi>Callicrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> which loſt a goodly fléete of the Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians with ouermuch haſt. We ſée the lingring ſnaile by tract of time doth ſoftly climing reach to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> toy of ſtately Towers, &amp; there quietly ſits without danger, where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fierce capitain with hot aſſaults &amp; bloudy ſkirmiſhe at laſte perhappes winnes the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:9019:29"/>
ſtrongeſt fort, which he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not kéepe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out double charge and deadlye perill. And ſurelye, the cunning to kéepe is no leſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, than the courage to obtayne: And thus he that will rule, muſt learne to be obedient, he that will liue quietly, muſte of force reſtraine his affections, and hée that would be knowen to be a gentleman, muſt alwayes vſe good conditions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Selfe loue and ſurquidrie.</head>
               <head>CHAP. 5.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Can not eaſily condiſcende to the opinion of thoſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che affirme that a man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in any wiſe doe himſelfe wrong: but I am rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by reaſon to beléeue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man can hurte no man ſo muche, as hée plagueth himſelfe. For if we conſider the miſerable eſtate of mankinde, ſubiecte to ſuch and ſo many fearefull daungers and ſodaine alterations, in the whole courſe of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:9019:30"/>
his life: we ſhall finde that in ſteade of one iniurie done is another man, he bringeth mountaines of care, &amp; heapes of ſorrowes vpon his owne head. And to omitte all chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh ſorrowes, when he commeth from his crade firſt into riper yeres of diſcreation, good God, howe violently is he drawen by ſwéete alluring luſte, into the lothſome practiſe of follye? what care vexeth him within? what feare doth compaſſe him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute? what pleaſures in hope? what ſorrowes in diſpaire? what flames of deſire? and what colde floudes of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine? and finallye, what rockes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe doe breake the billow waues of his wauering minde; in ſo muche as tenne thouſande times in a daye (to ende this careful ſtrife) he calles for deathe to cutte the line aſunder, of this his luck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe life. And yet perhaps by tract of time he is taughte to leaue ſuch toyes: reaſon peraduenture maye rule ſuche rage, and counſayle ouercome ſuche youthfull fanſies. But from thence eſcaping the daunger of <hi>Scilla,</hi> hée is
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:9019:30"/>
nowe throwne headlong vppon the dreadfull rockes of <hi>Charibdis:</hi> he is growne from youth to manhoode: naye rather he is come from ioye to greife, from pleaſure to paine, and from myrth to miſchiefe: before the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton deſires of youthe moleſted him, but nowe the wilfull déedes of manhoode, doe dayly aſſaulte him: before the pleaſure of luſte enticed him to follye, but nowe the rage of wrathe can prouoke him to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, he was then rauiſhed with the ioyes of heauen, but nowe he is haunted with furies of Hell. For in in this age he is chiefely ſubiect to pride, vexed with wrath, and puft, or rather poyſoned with ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Againe when the naturall heate of luſtie youthfull blonde, by diminiyſhing, ſéemes to moderate ſuche outragious furies, to qualitie ſuche affections, and to aſſwage all ſuche wylfull deſyres: Euen then commes the Image of deathe (I meane olde age) ſo crooked, ſo lame, ſo deformed, ſo lothſome,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:9019:31"/>
fraught with ſuch care, and ouerlade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſuch infirmities, that a man would wiſhe rather nowe to dye liuing, than to lyue longer in ſuch a plight pyning: for beſides all theſe plagues and tedious annoyes, it is moſt commonly accompanyed with ſuche a diueliſhe companion, that fainteth hys weake bodie for want of ſuſtenaunce, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieteth his teſtie minde for lacke of reſte, and in the end (like and euil guide that leads a blinde man into the ditche) it cloſeth vp his eyes in endleſſe ſorrowes and moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable calamities. And this is the ſame couetouſneſſe, which hath bin euer accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the roote of all miſchiefes. So that wée ſée by the whole courſe of humain life, that a manne is the chiefeſt enemye vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. And oftentimes it commeth to paſſe, that where a man ſoweth pleaſure, he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth paine, where he pretendeth loue, he findeth hate: and wherein he ſéemes to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende others leaſt, he priuilye hurteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf moſt.<note place="margin">Philautia.</note> And this is manifeſtly proued by the example of Self loue and ſurquedry A ſwéete vice and deceiteful affection is that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:9019:31"/>
fanſie which the Philoſophers haue called <hi>Philautia,</hi> and ſo naturall a diſeaſe in déed, that neyther Prince nor Péere, highe nor lowe, rich nor poore, wiſe nor fooliſh, weak nor ſtrong, faire nor deformed, no not the learned Philoſophers themſelues, were all able to withſtand. And me thinkes I heare Nature thus reaſoning with my ſelfe: Is it poſſible for a man to liue that loues not himſelfe beſt? but that is contrarie to my lawes, which haue giuen to euerye one an eſpecial charge and prouident care to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh himſelfe: and that thou mayſt eaſilye perceyue this to be true, beholde I gaue thée eares to heare, eyes to ſée, tongue to ſpeake, reaſon to vnderſtande, féete to goe, handes to féede and defend thy ſelf, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally care to maintayne the good eſtate of life. Theſe things are grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by kind, and canſt thou vndkindlye ſéeke to abuſe them, more to the profit of others than to thine own benefit? no not if thou wouldeſt: for I can compell thée to the contrarie: but thou takeſt more delight in the beautie of another: I graunt, ſo thy neyghbours field
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:9019:32"/>
is more fruitful, and his cattell beare more bountifull vdders, and what fares ſhe the worſe for that, whiche féedes ofte vpon the ſame, and thinkes hir owne birdes fayreſt? So can I ſée them wéepe when I laughe, mourne when I reioice, ſicke when I am whole, poore when I am riche, naked when I am clothed, impriſoned when I am frée, and harbourleſſe when I am houſed: and wherein can this be hurteful vnto me whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che féele not an other mans griefe, knowe not his wante, nor beare not his paſſion? but what if I did? ſhoulde I ſupporte hys néede, and waſte mine owne wealth? that were folly: ſhoulde I ſette hym frée to loſe mine owne libertie? that were more vaine: and generally, ſhoulde I ſuccoure him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue and cure his diſeaſe? to hinder me, to grieue me, and increaſe mine own ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies? that were euen little better than madneſſe. No, I am neareſt vnto my ſelfe, and therefore no man can iuſtly blame me, to prefer mine owne ſafetie before the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of an other: and I may perhaps commend him wel, and like hir bette, but
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:9019:32"/>
I will euer loue my ſelfe beſte.</p>
               <p>To theſe obiections of nature, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falſe perſwaſions of Diuelliſhe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, reaſon doeth modeſtlye replye, by the aucthoritye of trueth, in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>Howe long wilte thou abuſe the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of diuine power, Oh thou frowarde and peruerſe humaine Nature? how long ſhall thy proude lookes prouoke the dreade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wrath of the heauens? canſt thou ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chalenge the name &amp; title of a goddeſſe, and yet ſtill practiſe to rebell againſte the Lawes and ordinaunces of the Goddes? or wilte thou looke to be called the mother of mankinde, and wilt not ſubmit thy ſelfe to the rules of reaſon? doth not the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudgement of the one, feare thée from ſinne? nor the friendly perſwaſions of the other, moue to imbrace vertue? But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what thou art of thy ſelfe, yet at the length I beſéeche thée: haſte thou anye ſtrength, ſubſtaunce, beautie, reaſon, or vnderſtandyng, whyche is not giuen thée from aboue? A naked life in déede
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:9019:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
we receiue at thy handes: and what auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that vnto vs without good conditions, nay, were it not better to be vnfed, than vntaught and neuer borne, than broughte vp to deſtruction? Thou vaunteſt of life: but canſt thou make vs frée from deathe? thou talkeſt of beautie, but ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt thou teach vs to auoyde the ſmart of luſte? thou brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt of ſtrength, but canſt thou warrant vs to w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtand ſickneſſe? no nor any meanes thou canſt ſée to make vs thy childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie. For as he is not called fortunat which is poore and deformed, ſo they are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted happye, which are onely rich and beautifull. But thou wilt ſaye perhappes, that Nature is deſirous of knowledge whiche is the grounde worke and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Wiſdome: And it is true that a man is naturally inclined to the practiſe of ſkill, and experience of cunning: For in his youth hée voluntarilye learneth to ſpeake, then he practiſeth to diſpute, and perſwade, hée learneth to delighte with ſoundes, hée is taught to number anye ſummes, hée meaſureth the grounde
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:9019:33"/>
by proportions, and ruleth the ſtars with vnderſtanding: And what profiteth a man to compaſſe al the worlde by witte, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy himſelfe for want of wiſdome? for as life without learning is vnpleaſant, ſo lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning without Wiſdome is vnprofitable. To what ende ſerued the déepe knowledge of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> whiche vertuouſly inſtructed others, and yet deſperately ſhortned hys owne life? what aualyed the profounde ſkil of <hi>Archimedes,</hi> whiche loſte his Citie beſiedged by <hi>Marcellus</hi> and was himſelfe (then drawing out of circles) by a meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſodainely put to death? And what gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Plato</hi> by his learning, whiche was ſhamfully reproued of ambition? likewiſe of the reſt <hi>Narciſſus</hi> was faire and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, but his vnhappye fauour was the cauſe of his deſtruction: and laſtly, <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> and <hi>Sampſon</hi> were ſtrong, but not able to withſtande the force of ſhamefull death. And thus you ſée to vaine &amp; vitious nature the proude bloſſomes of your vntimelye fruit, ſoone withered: the ſtrength of youre aucthoritie, ſoone decayed: and the beautie
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:9019:34"/>
of your countenaunce ſooneſt of all to be fledde, forlorne, and defaced.</p>
               <p>And ſurelye, if a man woulde but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der eyther the imperfections of nature, the innumerable ſorrowes of thys lyfe, or the inuincible force of death, no doubt hée ſhoulde be as earneſtlye perſuaded to folowe the rule of ryght, and ſéeke out the ſecretes of wyſedome, as hée was firſt allured to ſwéete ſinne, and violentlye drawen into the ſchoole of follye. But alas, thoſe which are in hell knowe not the ioyes of heauen: and what hope of victorie is left to them that are alreadie conquered? O ſtrong ſelfe Loue, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent force of pryde, what homicyde, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricyde, or what murthers haſte thou not committed? What flamyng fyres, what warres, yea what miſchiefe haſte thou not attempted? Thou haſt killed Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, poyſoned Kynges, and murthered moſt famous Emperours: By thée ſtrong Caſtles are raſed, townes ſpoyled, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties waſted, and by thée countreys are lefte deſolate. And whither can the force
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:9019:34"/>
of thy ragyng furie bée nowe further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended? Thou haſte vanquiſſhed men, and wylt thou nowe exercyſe thy tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye vpon brute beaſtes? And woulde to GOD we myght all bée ſo well excuſed. Thou haſte wonne the whole worlde, but doeſt thou meane to laye ſiege to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens? or giue battyle vnto the Gods? But remember thy Champion Lucifer, what rewarde had hée for hys proude at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte? Call to mynde the preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous buildynges of <hi>Nembroth,</hi> and what ſucceſſe had hée in hys enterpryſe: And forget not the proude Knyght <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> whiche being valiaunt and fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in warres, had ſuche confidence in hys courage, and ſuche faythfull truſte in hys owne ſtrength, that hée ſcorned at thoſe (whiche after victorie obteyned) dyd vſe anye ceremonyes in worſhipping of their Goddes, callyng it a cowardlye affection that fearefullye craued helpe and ſupporte of ſhadowes: but hée was ſodainly conſumed with fyre from heauen,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:9019:35"/>
beyng in the forefronte of the battayle at the ſiege of <hi>Thebes.</hi> Theſe thynges conſidered, maye ſoone coole the hote cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of pryde, and moſte horryble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptes of Surquedrye. But the cloſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of ſelfe Loue is more couertlye crepte into the opinions of men, whiche thinke them ſelues by nature bounde, and not forbydden by diuyne lawes to make muche of them ſelues. And God forbyd but that eche man ſhoulde haue a proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent care to profite hime ſelfe: But yet are wée taught by the commaundements of GOD to loue another equallye as our ſelues: wée are inſtructed by the recorde of holye ſcriptures, that all our actions ought to be done to the glorie of GOD: And wée maye learne by prophane wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that wée are not borne vnto our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, but that partlye our parentes, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye friendes, partlye chyldren, partlye kynſefolke, and chiefelye our natyue countreye doeth chalenge a pryncypall duetie, wherin the charitable loue and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of vs all is ioyntly comprehended.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:9019:35"/>
And this is more plainly perceyued by the comfortable vertue of ſociete, without the which the life of man were naked, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and vnpleaſaunt: For what auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it vnto a man to be the monarche of the whole worlde, if he haue not ſubiects to gouerne, if hée haue not a wyfe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe his ofſpryng, if he haue not chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to honour and defende hym, and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if he haue not friendes to reioyce with hym in proſperitie, and to comfort hym in aduerſitie. Yea if hée be not happie, ſtraight wayes that hath all theſe things, howe vnhappie is he then that wanteth ſo many goodly commodities? And by this meanes a proude man is to bée thought moſt infortunate. For when he begins to take an opinion of him ſelfe, euen then is he firſt miſlyked of others: Where hée fawnes he is feared, where he loues hée is ſuſpected, where he fauours moſt he is leſt regarded: Agayne, when he frownes he is forſaken, when hée laughes he is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyed, and when hée mournes hée is left deſolate: But hée is warye and wyſe,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:9019:36"/>
hée wyll truſt none, neyther ſhall he be truſted of anye: hée is proude bycauſe hée is ryche, but hée is poore in that hée is proude: hée is ſtrong in power, but he is weake in wyſedome: hée is comelye in proportion, but hée is deformed in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Waye theſe thynges togyther in the true ballaunce of reaſon, and you ſhall perceyue the wayght of ſinne, and heauie burthen of miſchiefe, able to ſinke the ſtrongeſt, the comelieſt, and the prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt man alyue, into the deadlye pytte of deſtruction. <hi>Dioniſius</hi> was wyſe, and yet hée beguyled hym ſelfe, for hée was ſhamefullye murthered by the conſent of hys wyfe. <hi>Brennus</hi> was valiaunt, yet coulde not withſtande the wrath of the Gods. And <hi>Tarquinius</hi> was proude, but pryde was the cauſe of this foule deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And theſe be the fruites of ſelfe Loue &amp; Surquedrie. But ceaſe (O cruell Kyng) ceaſe nowe at length thys thy ragyng tyrannye, forbeare to vexe the myndes of innocentes with pryde, and drowne no
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:9019:36"/>
more vnhappie ſoules in the ſeas of ſelfe Loue and Surquedrie. And yet why doe I thus gentlye entreate with a Tyrant? why doe I pleade for peace with the chief authour of diſcorde? And whye doe I call hym Kyng, which is the father of miſchiefe, and mortall enemye to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde euer ſince the begynnyng of the worlde? Euen hym I meane, whyche brought the fyrſt care and calamityes vnto <hi>Adam</hi> by the taſte of an Apple. For it is none but hée whiche couertly ſéekes by falſe prouocations to bryng vs vnto miſchiefe: It is hée that ſettes the ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full plantes of pryde, and hée that ſowes the moſte hatefull ſéede of diſſention: But hée nameth hym ſelfe the Prince of the Worlde, howe ſhall wée than ſéeke to confounde hym? Naye but hée is the Father of lyes, and therefore we wyll not belieue hym: hée is but a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, and why ſhoulde wée then feare him? he triumpheth ouer worldlings lyke a Lyon, but reſiſt him ſtoutlye and hée
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:9019:37"/>
vaniſheth into nothyng. Wylt thou learne to withſtande the temptations of Sathan? Then you muſt faithfully cleaue to the promyſe of God, whiche will not ſuffer the righteous to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded. But thou canſt not be righteous of thy ſelfe, nor faythfull without humilitie, nor hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble without charitie: For theſe vertues are vnyted and can not bée ſeparated. So that hée whiche woulde haue the fauour of the diuine Maieſtie, muſt néedes inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour hym ſelfe to reſiſt the ſtrength and power of our vniverſal enemye. Neyther is it too late at any tyme to reſorte vnto goodneſſe, nor too tymelye to preuent miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes. Wée muſt vſe no procraſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and delayes to be vertuous. <hi>For hee that is not readye to thinke well to daye, will be more vnlikely to doe good on the morrowe.</hi> And it is not enough to thinke ill of none, but wée (muſt in that we may) doe good vnto all, yea euen vnto our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes, for thus are wée taught to doe good for euyl, which are the fruites of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect charitie. Much leſſe then ought we to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:9019:37"/>
disdayne them that honour vs, to ſpoyle them that ſerue vs, to perſecute them that loue vs, neyther to muſel the mouth of the labouryng Oxe, nor vniuſtly to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe the rewardes of well deſerued hier: for theſe are the workes of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie. Therefore if nature haue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what heretofore nuſled vs in the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe affections of ſelfe Loue, which is the authour of pryde, and conſequently, the cauſe of great miſchiefe: yet let vs hencefoorthe followe the perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of reaſon, whyche teacheth vs to ſhunne the vaine enticementes of follie, and to ſearche out the diuine ſecretes of wiſedome. and ſurelye the firſt point hereof, in myne opinion, is for a man to knowe hym ſelfe. It is ſtraunge that the nature of man ſhoulde be deſirous of nouelties, and not regarde his owne ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or that his minde ſhoulde be able to diſcouer the qualitie of the heauens, and yet graueled in the knowledge of himſelf: but you will ſay, it is an eaſie matter for a man to bée knowen from a beaſte,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:9019:38"/>
and that is by reaſon and vnderſtanding. Then what meant the Philoſopher <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diogenes</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the Market place ſtoode gazing amongſt a multitude, and being deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded whome he ſought, made anſwere, that he loked if he mighte ſée anye man: they told him, that there were manye, but hée ſayde agayne, verily amongſt ſo many, I can not finde anye man: for he accompted them no men, which coulde not rule theyr affections, whiche in the common ſorte of people is not eaſie to be founde, when of the learned themſelues, it is a rare thing to be followed. And as it is ſayd, <hi>the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Clearkes are not alwayes the wyſeſt men,</hi> nor commonly, <hi>the ſtrongeſt moſte valiant.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note> And as the higheſt trées are more ſubiect to the bluſtering force of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> winds, than the low ſhrubbes, which are ſhrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnder the defence of the Mountaines, ſo the noble mindes of Princes, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Péeres, are ſooner ſhadowed and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt with the clowdes of Vanitie, than the quiet fanſies of the meaneſt, whoſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are gouerned by the ſtedfaſt rule
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:9019:38"/>
of Vertue. And for this cauſe it was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily prouided by the Emperoures of olde tyme, that the ſame daye they were crowned, euen in their chiefe royaltie, the artificers ſhoulde come perſonally, and demaunde how and after what ſorte it woulde pleaſe him to haue his Tombe faſhioned: and this was done ſolemnely, to the intente he ſhoulde be mindfull of death, and not ſurpriſed with too muche delighte of ſuddayne felicitie. Therefore, if Princes and Emperoures haue not bin aſhamed to acknowledge themſelues mortall, and by this meanes, to ſuppreſſe the ſwelling waues of vayne glory, it behoueth all priuate men muche more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilantly to watche and warde, that they bée not at anye time puffed vp, and infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wyth the ſtrong poyſon of ſelfe loue, and moſt hatefull ſurquedrie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:9019:39"/>
               <head>Of Wine and Women.</head>
               <head>CHAP. 6.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eliodorus</hi> in the thyrde Booke of hys Ethiopian Hiſtorie, proueth, that the cauſe of intemperancy and luſt, are both one, for as well (ſayth he) the mind of a drunken man is flexible, as the affections of loue are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, bycauſe they are both drowned in moyſt humors: and therefore we ſée, that a common louer wil ſoone be drunke, and a drunkerde ſoone moued with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of loue. It were a doubtfull queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to determine, whether hathe grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter force, of Wyne or Women, for ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, the ſtrength of the one is inuincible, and the luſt of the other not to be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed.</p>
               <p>Thys conquereth Kings, that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth whole countreys: this deſguiſeth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into beaſtes, &amp; that tranſformeth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into Monſters. This diuorceth vs from the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:9019:39"/>
ioyes of Heauen, and that other winds vs to paines of Hell. But leaſt we ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende with <hi>Tireſias,</hi> we will rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe with the Chamberlaine of <hi>Darius,</hi> that in theſe poyntes women are ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne. And as the vſe of them both, and many things elſe is very neceſſarie, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and profitable, ſo it is only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abuſe, eyther of them, or anye thing, that is fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, tedious, and incoueniente. May not the trée be good, although the bloſſoms are blaſted? is not the ayre wholſome, bycauſe it is hurtful to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſickly? or is gold naught, bycauſe our nature is corrupted? no, it is pure, but we are vnperfect: theſe thyngs are wholeſome, but we are immoderate: they are good, but our affections are euill diſpoſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> gaue counſell to King <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> in his moſt troubleſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres, and warlike aduentures, to behold the beautifull countenance of women, and by pleaſant ſpéeche with them had, to lighten the weight of cares, which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually increaſing, mighte diſcourage the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:9019:40"/>
mind of the moſt valiante from his noble enterpriſe: wherein he had great reaſon, for what can be more delectable vnto a man, than to behold the image of himſelf, ſette forth in a more perfect and heauenly figure? what more comfortable, than to ſée the cauſe of his life, and conſequently, the chiefe authour of his felicitie? what is more ioyfull than pleaſure? what more pleaſant than beautie? and what can bée more beautifull than women? ſurely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. And I ſuppoſe with the Poets, that Nature hath curiouſly faſhioned them in hir owne molde, with ſuche excellencie of perſonage, to ſpite the proude Goddeſſe, that vauntes hir ſelfe in beautie to be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne. Neyther can I perceyue them in any vertues to be much inferiour vnto men, but if I ſhoulde not ſpeake partiall, rather the authours, than followers of wiſedome. To beginne with Chaſtitie, it is not poſſible that ſo pure a mettall ſhuld be defiled with anye ſpottes of filthy luſt, for why? they were made after the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of man, of the ſoundeſt parte of hys
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:9019:40"/>
body. Moreouer, their owne complexion is cold, and therefore commonly they are more temperate and chſt, modeſt and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, milde and mercifull, moſt conſtant and pitifull, and for the corruption that ariſeth of groſſe meates, and vnholeſome ſauoures, why they haue by nature a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall euacuation of all ſuperfluous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moures, ſuche force hathe that whiche is pure, to expell the ſame that is vncleane. And what is he that doubtes of the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie of women? but let him remember onely the daughter of <hi>Virginius,</hi> whyche choſe rather to be ſlayne of hir owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than to hazarde the Caſtell of hyr chaſtitie, vnto the hote ſéege of <hi>Appius</hi> hir fleſhly enimie: if they be not conſtante, what was <hi>Penelope?</hi> if not patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, what was <hi>Griſeld?</hi> if not pitifull, what was <hi>Dido?</hi> excepte you will make them God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſes for Vertue, whyche were in déede by kynde women: but you wyll ſay, they wante courage, bycauſe they are gentle by nature: a wiſe reaſon, as though Sainctes themſelues are not ſometymes
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:9019:41"/>
diſpleaſed, or as if the water were not calmeſt in the déepe, and the winde ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geir in the ſtreyghts: but dyd not Quéene <hi>Thomiris</hi> chalenge the combat of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> to fighte with him hande to hande, whiche he refuſed? was not <hi>Pentheſeleia</hi> before hir in the middeſt of the battell at the ruinous ſéege of <hi>Troy?</hi> what was <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lona</hi> hir ſelfe, if women were not coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious? yes no doubt, they are ſtrong and valiante, whiche appeareth euen in that ſtout affection of them, whiche burneth in deſire of ſoueraintie. And laſtly, for wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is it like that <hi>Pallas</hi> would inſtruct me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſpitefully withdraw fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir owne ſexe, the worthy gift of vnderſtanding? no, but it is manifeſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe hath adopted them for hir only heires, of ſuch a right &amp; boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful patrimonie, which benefit men haue rather receiued at their hands, than fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out by their owne induſtries. For it is thoughte that the Latines firſte learned their leters of <hi>Nicoſtrata. Pithagoras</hi> was ſuppoſed to be the deſciple of hys ſiſter <hi>Theoclea. Pericles</hi> the Duke of <hi>Athens</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:9019:41"/>
was inſtructed in learning by <hi>Aſpatia.</hi> Suche and abſolute perfection of vertue, and ſo rare a figure of diuine beautie, is both fixed, and faſhioned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noble mind, and comely proportion of women, that who can miſtruſt any lothſome qualities to lurke vnder the couerte ſhadowes of ſuch comelineſſe, but thoſe which haue by experience vnhappily found the ſame to be manifeſt? But oh blind goddeſſe Fortune, or curſed furie Fate, with what tearmes ſhall I enter into thy diſprayſe? with what voyce ſhall I ſound thy diſhonour? or by what force ſhall I confound thy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement? thou that vnequally diuideſt thy goodes, thou that partially beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt thy giftes, and thou that diſdeyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully rewardeſt thy ſubiectes, why diddeſt thou not indifferently impart riches vnto men, that none ſhould be diſdeyned? or v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſally beſtowe vertues on women, that none mighte be condemned: bycauſe thou wilt ſay, the laſt was not in my po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and the firſte was not conueniente. But is it nature then, that hathe thus
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:9019:42"/>
ſcornefully abuſed hir creatures? to rayſe vp one vnto the ſeate of honourable fame, and to foyle a thouſand with the reproche of ſhamefull follie? Surely it were an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt parte of a mother, that had manye daughters, to make one of them hir Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, and all the reſt hir ſeruantes. And it were vnnaturall in a Nurſſe (in ſtead of Milke) to giue hir children poyſon. But Nature is the mother of mankinde, and teacheth to maynteyne the commodities of life: ſhe is oure Nurſſe, and therefore wiſheth the health of hir children. No, it is euen oure ſelues, that are corrupte and imperfect, it is menne that are abuſed by women, and it is women that are the cauſe of all miſchiefe. Examine hiſtories (whyche are the light of truth) euen from the begynning of the worlde vntill thys day, and you ſhall finde no griefe, no ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, no deathe, no danger, no warres, no waſt, no fiers, no deſtruction, no woes, no lamenting, no deceypt, falſehode, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, no not anye other inconuenience, whereof a woman hath not bin ſome part
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:9019:42"/>
of the occaſion. Was not <hi>Eue</hi> the cauſe of Originall Sinne? than the whyche to mankynde, what coulde happen more pernicious? thys one ſingular example of moſte auntiente authoritie, myghte ſerue to daunte the pryde, and coole the vauntyng bragges of wicked and licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious women: for as they beganne with perſuaſions of falſe delyghte, ſo they continue wyth diſſembling practiſe, and ende commonly wyth horrible ſhamefull miſchiefe.</p>
               <p>Theyr begynning I call the floures of youth, whyche age is fyrſte ſubiecte to the manye aſſaultes of loue, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in howe maydenly they behaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the mayntenance of Virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nay, howe Syrenelyke they ſhewe themſelues, in the Shipwracke of theyr modeſtie, it is wonderfull. And firſte, ſhe learnes to ſet hir eies, fixed with the ſtars in ſigne of ſtabilitie: hir eares are vigila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to heare hir ſelf praiſed: hir tong is taught to be ſilente, in token of modeſtie: hyr
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:9019:43"/>
countenance is milde, hir ſpéech ſhort and ſwéete, and laſtly hir liuely lookes of ſober chéere, but yet amiable. She is baſhfull, &amp; therefore ſittes moſt comely beneath at the dore, or elſe aboue ſomewhat more modeſtly in a windowe, where ſhe ſings ſometimes for ſorow, ſhe ſighes perhaps for delighte, ſhe ſowes for a faſhion, ſhée playes to remoue fanſies, &amp; ſhe mournes for want of company. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes to be moued with playne tearmes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, good God what niceneſſe ſhe wyll vſe, how coy ſhe will become, and what a countenance of virginitie ſhe will bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, to ſet forth the matter, for then they will all be Nunnes, they will neuer mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, nor knowe what a man meanes, ſo long as they liue, whereas they meane nothing ſo muche as the contrarye: but lette them be courted after another ſorte, and as you would ſaye, proffer them the common courteſie, it is not ſo ſoone offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as willingly enterteyned: for when they know the depth of his deuotion, they ſound his affection by their owne deſire, &amp;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:9019:43"/>
they ſuppoſe he will be quickly loſt, if not lightely loued: and thus they féede ſome wyth lookes, and other with loue: ſome wyth wordes, and other with workes: ſome with ſporte, and other with ſpite: ſome with pleaſure, ſome with payne: ſome with fauoure, ſome with diſdeyne: ſome with loſſe, ſome with gayne, that I thinke their inſatiable deſire would haue as many ſupplyes, as they haue ſleightes of alluring. And theſe are the ſlighte prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes of yong women, whome when riper yeares, and alteration of eſtate hath well grounded in the perfection of their ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, then they begin to procéede in high degrées of falſehoode. By this time vſe hath made them experte, and impudence hath giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vtterance of déepe diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling flatterie, but now they haue a cloke for the rayne, and why ſhoulde they bée baſhfull? before they maſked in the cloſe viſordes of virginitie, but nowe they daunce with the figure, a Saincte in their hande, and the image of Diuels in theyr heart: before they were onely moleſted
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:9019:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
with the tyrannie of loue, but nowe they are vexed with hate, preſſed with pryde, poyſoned with diſdeyne, haunted with iealouſie, and plagued with ſuſpition, and the leaſt of them all (if it lay in their power) is as muche as a mans lyfe is worth, for the nature of them all is in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames, in ſo muche, that eyther they loue affectionately, whiche is ſeldome, or elſe they hate deadly (whyche is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon:) they are too proude or too ſluttiſhe, too fonde or too frowarde, too pleaſaunte or too péeuiſhe, too muche fawning or too ſcornefull, too much familiar or too ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, too ſhéepiſhe or too ſhrewiſhe, too apiſh or too lumpiſhe: ſo that all their affections are without meane, and theyr paſſions without meaſure, as ſoone ſurpriſed in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, &amp; as ſoone confounded with ſorrow, ſoone quickned with hope, and as ſoone drowned in deſpayre, ſoone wéeping, ſoone laughing, and accordyng to the Prouerb,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Soone ripe, ſoone rotten,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſeldome ſeene, is ſoone forgotten.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:9019:44"/>They are Lawleſſe, for they chooſe whome they like, and refuſe when they liſt: but yet they are conſcionable, for they woulde haue all thinges in common. So they are liberall, but it is of other mens goodes: they are pitifull, bycauſe they would haue no man wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that which they deſire: &amp; they are courteous, bycauſe they would be courted. <hi>Mantuan</hi> likeneth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a Northeaſt winde, whiche beareth off cloudes at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt puffe, and drawes them back again with a falſe encou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tring blaſt. So wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they perceiue the deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be cold, or their owne beautie to be diminiſhed by tract of time, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> begins the knowledge of their cunning to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, &amp; the full perfection of arte to bée practiſed: they will not haue their ſmooth browes with vntimely wrincles to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, nor their comely chéekes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roſeal coulour ſo ſone to be defrauded, it wer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt to ſuffer their beauty to decay for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of repratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chief cauſe of their maintenance. How ſhould they be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for images, vnles they be curiouſly pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:9019:45"/>
how ſhould they be taken for Sainctes, if they were not gorgeouſly attired? and how ſhoulde they be honoured for Goddeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, if gliſtering in golde, the maieſtie of their perſon ſhould not be fully furniſhed? yea, they kembe, they curle, they pinke, they purle, they ſtreyne, they fayne, they wrinch, they pinch, and all to inſinuate ſo fine a carcaſſe with alluring lookes, into the practiſe of follie. And dare you call them weake, which in force haue vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the ſtrongeſt? and no maruell, for what man hathe euer bin ſo ſtrong, but hathe bin vanquiſhed by fonde deſires of luſt? had <hi>Hercules</hi> bin burned? had <hi>Giges</hi> bin ſlayne? hadde <hi>Dioniſius</hi> bin murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? had <hi>Anchus,</hi> the ſonnes of <hi>Arcinoë, Cyrus,</hi> and other innumerable Kings and Princes, dyed of miſchiefe, but by the onely treaſon of women? what ſhoulde I ſpeake of warres, ſith <hi>Troy,</hi> the chiefe Citie of all <hi>Aſia,</hi> was for a womans ſake ſackt, waſted, and lefte, deſolate? I loth to recite Paricides, though <hi>Scilla</hi> murthered hir father <hi>Niſus,</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:9019:45"/>
and caried his heare for a ſigne of loue to his enimie King <hi>Minos,</hi> which ſcorneful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gift and abhominable giuer, ſuch are the frutes of luſt, and outragious deſires of women. And are they to bée thought ſimple, which in wiles haue begi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the wiſeſt? and true it is, for who hath euer bin deceyued, where he hathe neuer faithfully truſted? and whome ſhuld a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truſt, if not his owne wife, with whome he liues, for whome he toyles, in whom he ioyes, and from whome he ſhould receyue moſt loyal loue, and moſt comfortable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light? But alas, in ſtead of comforte, they giue care to their huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, in ſtead of ioy, they bring ſorrow, for meate mourning, for drinke dolor, for reſt vnquietneſſe, for ſafety perils, for peace diſcord, and at laſt, for his good deſertes, he is requited with the vile rewarde of miſchiefe. Was not <hi>Albinus</hi> the firſte King of the <hi>Lombardes,</hi> ſhamefully murthered by his faire ſpouſe <hi>Roſamund?</hi> was not <hi>Agamemnon</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued after the ſame ſorte wyth hys vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt wife <hi>Clytemneſtra?</hi> howe ſpedde
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:9019:46"/>
the wiſeſt of them all? Were not <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Dauid, Caeſar, Antonius, Tully, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Aurelius</hi> and others, abuſed by the ſleightes of their wiues and women? And therefore who is nowe ſo fonde but wyll learne to bridle the affections of luſt? who is ſo blinde that ſées not the falſe entyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of follie? and who ſo doltiſhe that will doate vppon ſuche kytes of <hi>Creſides</hi> kynde? It is better with <hi>Phirimus</hi> the beautifull young <hi>Romaine,</hi> to deface the Maieſtie of comely fauour and beautie, than with <hi>Narciſſus</hi> to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded with his owne follie: it is more commendable with <hi>Alexius</hi> to forſake the concupiſence of the fleſhe, and folow the ſwéete contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of wiſedome, than with vnhappie <hi>Cephalus</hi> to ſéeke the tryall of faithleſſe folke, and fal into the ſnares of ineuitable miſchiefe. But in any wyſe I would not haue the vertuous women &amp; modeſt vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines herewith offended: For the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of Vice increaſeth the glorie and prayſe of Vertue, none otherwyſe, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beautie of the ſwéete Roſe more brauelye
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:9019:46"/>
ſhewes it ſelfe being ſet amongſt Nettles, and the Sunne appeareth more glorious in ſight after the darke clowdes and drou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng ſhades of nyght is baniſhed. And to the reſt I tel this tale to ſtop their own en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious conceit, &amp; ſelf hurting imagination. There was a Lady of baſe birth, &amp; borne in a barbarous countrey, which by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of blinde fortune was raiſed vnto the ſtage of honour, wherein bluntly behauing hir ſelf, aſwel towardes hir equals as infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, ſhée was generally miſlyked of all ſortes, in ſomuche as hir huſbande alſo at length began to eſtrange himſelf vnto hir, whoſe ſad lokes ſhe ouer haſtily ſuſpecting, or whither it be that a continual feare vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the guiltie minde (I cannot tell) but ſhe runnes haſtily to méete a ſecret friende of hirs which was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fields with his gown in his neck, &amp; a lame Crow whoſe wings he had maimed in his hand, and ſodainely bemoned hir caſe vnto hym howe infortunate ſhe was to be ſuſpected without cauſe, with an ample diſcourſe of hir miſfortunes: The Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowing
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:9019:47"/>
hir diſeaſe to haue procéeded onelye from the ielouſie of hir own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceit, had thought to haue giuen hir good counſaile in playne termes, but he was diſappoynted by the comming of hir huſband, which ſodeinelye came vpon them vnwares, and therfore he gaue hir this riddle for an anſwere before hir huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds face: Madam ſaith he, you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund what was the cauſe that I ſpoiled this carren Crowe which as you ſay was innocent, &amp; true it is, but yet ſitting in the top of a trée ſafely ſhrowded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſight, ſhée could not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent, but diſcouered hir ſelf by hir owne naturall voice, which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant for any man to heare: And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath bin ſubiect to this miſchance as you ſée, whereof in my iudgement hir ſelfe hath bene the chiefe occaſion. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſmiling, they went in all togither, &amp; the Gentleman rounding in hir eare, thus expounded his ridle. So Madam I doubt (ſayeth hée) that the too muche declinyng vnto your owne natural diſpoſition, hath bene the onely cauſe that the winges of your worthie Fame are now galled with
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:9019:47"/>
the ſpitefull ſhotte of ſuſpition. And ſurely ſo it falles out many tymes wyth thoſe (which are not very cunning diſſemblers) that while they intende to coulour theyr craft by diſſimulation, they vnwarily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer them ſelues by the force of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall affection, for <hi>nature is aboue arte in the ignorant:</hi> And Vertue aboue all things is eſtéemed of the wyſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Dyce play.</head>
               <head>CHAP. 7.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S there be dyuers &amp; ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry exerciſes of the bodye which are holeſome, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both ſtrength is worthily increaſed, and health as warily mainteyned: So there be many vnprofitable ſportes, vnlawfull games, and leude practiſes, which infecte the body with diſeaſes, pollute the minde with vices, ſpoile y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neceſſary goodes with vnthriftineſſe, and therefore ought of all
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:9019:48"/>
men to be ſhunned and aboliſhed. For if we make our ſporte and game to delyght, why ſhoulde wée toyle ſo muche therein moſte commonlye to our owne hynde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce and diſeaſe: but in loſſe is no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyght, in payne is no pleaſure, neyther is there anye ioye in annoye, and as the Poete ſayeth, <hi>Voluptatis commendat rarior vſus. <hi>The rare practice and ſeldome vſe commendeth pleaſure moſte.</hi>
                  </hi> Lette vs take for example amongeſt ſo manye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnprofitable diſportes, the only im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate vſe of Dyce playe, wherein if the pleaſure be little, the profite is leſſe: if the chaunce bée doubtfull, the choyce is harde: and thoughe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities are vncertayne, yet the dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profites are infinite. And firſt tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng the Fame and creadyte of a man whyche amongeſt the vertuous is eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med equall wyth lyfe: It is a verye harde matter inordinatly to followe the deceyptfull practiſe of this cooſenyng ſkyll or ſkilfull cooſenage, without the ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full marke of reproche or badge of open
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:9019:48"/>
infamye. For (beſides that many times hée is conſtrayned to diſappoynt hys eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall good friendes of ſundrye dayes of paiment) he ſhall be forced to make ſuche ſhiftes of deſcant and hard ſupplies to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derprop and bolſter his baſe eſtate, that at the yeares ende he ſhalbe driuen to fly, not for feare of his enemyes, but leaſt hée be purſued of his beſt friendes, and to ſhroud hym ſelfe in corners farre from the ſight of the ſcornefull. And is it not a ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thyng in déede that the abſence of friendes ſhoulde be deſired, and not their moſte comfortable preſence embraced? O moſte miſerable eſtate, where friendes are feared, and enemyes nothyng myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted: And howe farre from punyſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, can hée be whoſe countenaunce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraieth hym ſelfe guiltie? how farre from iudgement whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience accuſeth him? and how frée from impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t can he be which is in euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s debt &amp; danger? And thus is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fame &amp; good name of euerye man no ſooner in queſtion, than when he is kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to be a common gameſter. Then
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:9019:49"/>
then folowes the riotous effuſion of hys goodes and landes, whiche is euen as la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable.<note place="margin">Simile.</note> None otherwiſe than as in the ſhipwracke of a common wealth, or cruel ſpoile of a whole cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, where all things come to a moſt miſerable and ruinous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, euen ſo with theſe men, downe with woodes, downe with auncient buildyngs, downe with ſtately Towers, downe with Princely halles: And if it were in theyr power or poſſeſſion, whole ſtréetes, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, townes, Cities, and all ſhould goe downe euen flatte to the grounde. Why ſhould Pate be vnpauned and the owner lyke to be impriſoned? Why ſhould lands lye vnſolde and the Lorde lacke his liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? A courſe exchaunge of Plate for pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurie, and a ſhreude loſſe of landes and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie. But will ye knowe why Caſtles and Towers, Cities and townes, halles and houſes, landes, goodes, trées, and all goe to wracke? Surely bicauſe the Lorde is an vnthrift: And why be there nowe ſuche intruſions? why ſuche wrongfull poſſeſſors? why be rentes rackt without
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:9019:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
offence? why be tenaunts puniſht without cauſe? why ſuch pounding? why ſuche pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling? why ſuch ſtrayning? ſuch deteyning, ſuch driuyng, ſuch vnlawfull thryuing, ſuch catching, ſuche ſnatching, ſuche cooſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with quicke ſpéede, and ſuche falſhood nowe adayes in worde and déede? mary ſir bycauſe the Lord himſelfe hath néede. Oh luckleſſe Lorde with ſuche calamities mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted, and alas poore Tenaunts with ſuch a thriftleſſe landlord oppreſſed: were it not farre better to be the Tenaunt of libertie, than Landlorde of thrall? the ſeruaunte of thrift, than to be called Matter Makeſhift: and the ſcholler of Wiſdome, than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſlaue of Folly? Is it not vaine to followe ſuche a thriftleſſe vaine, that brings manye a welthy man to the Wallet? or is it not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurde for childiſhe paſtimes to forſake ſo many goodly commodities? or to be ledde by fond affections of youth, and léeſe the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of life? For beſides theſe greate loſſes of lande and liuing, perhappes in the ende he looſeth and deſtroyeth himſelfe, what with reare banquets, and more totheſome
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:9019:50"/>
tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> holeſome iunkets, what with vntime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly féeding and inſatiable quaffing, long ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, vnholeſome ſitting, night walkyng, and inordinate watching, he ſo muche di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempereth himſelfe, that of a moſt cleare complexion and healthfull bodie, he wyll in ſhorte ſpace be chaunged into a pale ghoſte haunted with greate ſickneſſe, and poyſoned with lothſome foule diſeaſes: This cauſeth the colde reumes (aſcending vppe into his careleſſe heade) to impaire the noble gifte of memorie, this dryueth downe the painefull goute into his féete, which griefe (almoſt incurable) depriues him of libertie, and this likewiſe bréedes the lothſome dropſie than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which nothing is more pernicious: and to be ſhorte, what other foule diſeaſes or any grieuous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies doeth not this diſorder bréede, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and maintaine? but yet they wyl ſay: what ſir, are we not yong and luſtie? and whye ſhoulde we then feare ſuche annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, as is more commonly ſubiect vnto age? doth the niceneſſe of women become vs? or ſhoulde we be curious in diet like
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:9019:50"/>
vnto Ladies? no, it hardneth vs to watche and faſte againſte we beare armour in the fielde: nay, (but by your leaue) vſing ſuche intemperance and diſorder, you may cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſooner to become a criple at Sainte Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelmewes in the ſpittle, than a ſouldiour with Saint George in the fielde: neyther is it womanly ſoftneſſe to auoyd ſickneſſe, nor wanton diet to ſéeke the meanes to preſerue health: But it is plaine follye to ſhorten the life by diſorder whiche by tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and modeſtie might better be che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and maintayned.</p>
               <p>From hence commes likewiſe ſuch ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, ſuch blaſpheming, ſuch fretting, ſuch fuming, ſuch brawling, ſuche blading, that oftentimes their ſolace is turned into ſin, their gaine into griefe, and their paſtimes into miſchiefe. But oh ye witleſſe folke, or wilfull youth, howe long ſhall theſe ſelfe-wrongs oppreſſe you? howe long wil you forſake true libertie, and ſéeke to be coupled in the ſtraight yoake of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage? for it is not fréedome to bée licentious, nor libertye to lyue Idle:
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:9019:51"/>
if you loue ſporte, is it not thereby to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light? but howe can that be pleaſaunt that is hurtefull? if thou ſéeke pleaſure is it not profitable vnto life? and why doe you then runne headlong vnto miſchiefe, but rather learne of Nature that life is moſte ſwéet, and remember the Poet <hi>Palengenius</hi> that ſaith, death ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by no meanes come too late. But to late co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes <hi>had I wiſt,</hi> walking in ſolitarie places, ſhunning the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of his familiars, and reaſoning wyth himſelfe like a man diſtraught out of hys ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes, with, what a wretch am I, that haue thus rigorouſly waſted my goods, impay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my good health, and hardly eſcaped the foule daunger and loſſe of life? why dyd I not erſte reſtraine ſuche fanſies? and why do I not yet follow the perſwaſions of good counſayl? but alas, late witte and vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Wiſdome, are the nexte neyghbours vnto folly. And perhappes while he is thus layde on his carefull bedde, complayning to himſelfe of his loſſe, the reſt of his play-fellowes haue friendly diuided the ſpoyle, and by this time huffing, ſcoffing and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:9019:51"/>
in ſtreates amongſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of their ruffianly companions. Is this a life or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther death? nay not ſo good, for death is the only ende of ſuche miſchiefe: then is it a moſt wretched life that is neuer frée from troubles.</p>
               <p>Therfore as the exerciſe of Chiualrye is profitable to the common wealthe, the practiſes of ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth and actiuitie, holeſome for the bodye: and the vſe of Dice, Cards, and other diſportes, good to recreate the minde: So the immoderate abuſe of them all, is not commendable, but hurtefull and pernicious, and therefore of all degrées and ſortes of people neceſſarye to bée refrayned and warelye eſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:9019:52"/>
               <head>Of Trauel.</head>
               <head>CHAP. 8.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt all the trades of life practiſed in ſundrye ſorte, ſince the beginning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, there is none more auntient and agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able vnto the Nature of man than Trauel. For as the foule is bred to flye, fiſh to ſwimme, the worme to créep, as naturally enclyned to that kind of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: So is man likewiſe addicted vnto la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and paines taking, euen from the firſt daye of his birth, vnto the laſt houre of his life. And as birdes flye not all one waye, but ſome to the hilles, other into the fieldes, and theſe vnto the water: Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo of diuerſe men diuerſe diſpoſitions, and not all inclyned to one conuerſation, and trade of liuing. For what common wealth (I pray ye) can conſiſt of one only Art and Societie? or what realme ſo ryche, what
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:9019:52"/>
nation ſo fertile, that néedeth no forraine help &amp; ſuggeſtion? Surely none ſo abſolute and perfect of it ſelfe, but ſhall daylye bée forced to ſéeke out &amp; willingly embrace the commodities of others, whyche howe can you attaine without Trauell? Then if the good eſtate of euery common wealth depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth much vpon trauell, no doubte the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent vſe thereof is no leſſe worthy to bée allowed and maintayned, than the greate and continuall commodities thereby got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, are gladly to be receyued and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. The which trade we ſée ſpecially to be maintayned and practiſed by thrée ſortes of men, that is, merchaunts, Legates, and aduenturers. To declare the effectes of them al, I thinke it not néedful, for though the gaines of the Merchaunts is great, yet I eſtéeme the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities &amp; glory of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be greater bicauſe how much it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth <hi>bene viuere quàm viuere,</hi> it is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> learned. Then ſparing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in their traffique, now we wil return to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Legates &amp; aduenturers, &amp; accompany the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only in this ſhort diſcourſe of Trauel.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:9019:53"/>
whoſe ſtudious minds in paineful trauel, hath fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time aſwell procured the quiet eſtate of this realme, as with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine treaſure wonderfullye enriched the ſame. Theſe therfore be they which dayly hazard themſelues, their liues, and all that they haue, in the faithfull ſeruice of their Prince &amp; country, which following y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſteps of famous Knights, and valiaunt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, account the wide circuite of the whole world, their own natiue ſoile, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallye, whiche for their ventrous actes and worthye mindes, deſerue to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, in the Bookes of euerlaſtyng memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
               <p>The noble charge of Embaſſage to bée of great waight and importaunce, I note eſpecially in theſe two points. Firſt by the dignitie of the perſon (who for the moſte part being out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> number of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, wiſe and learned ſorte) is alwayes no leſſe honourablye receyued, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thylye entertayned in the diſcharge of his Embaſſage. Againe, the moſte auntient vſe, and inuiolate cuſtome of libertie in all
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:9019:53"/>
landes by the lawe of armes graunted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Legates and Ambaſſadors, expreſly ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the great power and dignitie of their charge and calling. And firſte I take wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Herodotus,</hi> whiche writing of the continuall warres betwéene the Gretians and Barbarians, noteth for a wonder that ſhamefull fact of the Athenians, which vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a time did moſte villanouſly murder the Legates of <hi>Darius.</hi> But <hi>Xerxes</hi> ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pardoned their ſcouts (being taken and conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned by the Marſhall of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fielde) which before hadde murdred his fathers Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors. A notable example of Magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in a barbarous Prince, which diſdained the malice of his enimies.</p>
               <p>And to ſpeak of Trauel, we haue heard, that the auntient Pilgrims were wont to vſe manye ſuperſtitious ceremonies, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them al I note thrée ſpeciall points worthy and neceſſary to be vſed of all men. And firſte they had a guide to direct them: ſecondly they hadde commonlye a ſtaffe to ſtaye them: and laſtlye, they vſed to bathe their féete in the euening, that they mighte
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:9019:54"/>
we maye vſe for a ſtaffe to leane vnto in the daungers of Trauell. For if <hi>Iupiter</hi> himſelfe woulde vouchſafe to drawe vppe into Heauen ſome mortal wight, meaning to ſhewe hym all the celeſtiall ioyes &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the worlde, in vaine were the fruition and ſighte thereof vnto him (ſayth <hi>Cicero</hi>) vnleſſe he hadde ſome friende or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to whome he mighte imparte and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe theſe highe profits and commodities aforeſaid: wherevnto alludeth alſo the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et <hi>Iuuenall</hi> in this verſe, <hi>Sciretuum nihil est niſi te ſcire hoc ſciat alter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then ſith we are ſo naturally enclined to Societie, and that no friendeſhippe is to be compared to that which likeneſſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and diſpoſition hathe linked togither, whiche cauſeth equall mindes to be affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted either vnto other, whereby the true knotte of friendſhippe is knitte, according vnto <hi>Pithagoras,</hi> of one minde in two bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, it appeareth howe neceſſarie a thing is Societie and fellowſhippe in Trauaile, whiche <hi>Marcus Cicero</hi> hathe ſo fittely expreſſed in the perſons of <hi>Caius Lelius,</hi>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:9019:54"/>
and <hi>Publius Scipio Affricanus,</hi> that you woulde thinke them alyue familiarlye tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king wyth you, touching the friendſhippe betwéene them vſed, whiche not onelye in houſe and harboure, peace and warre, proſperitie and aduerſitie, but euen in long Peregrination and Trauaile was all one. And howe can the life of anye man be ſo ſolitarie, that he is not conſtrained to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighte in mutuall loue and ſocietie? what is more pleaſaunte than to haue ſo fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a friende, to whom thou maiſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte ſecreates as ſafely as to thy ſelfe, who in wrath doeth equally reioice, and in pouertie lament with thée? But here I doe not meane the common Familiaritie and good fellowſhyppe whyche is pretended nowe amongeſt diuers, nor of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affection of brothers and kinſfolkes, whiche euen nowe as in <hi>Ouides</hi> dayes, <hi>Fratrum quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> gratia rara est.</hi> But I meane the true and vertuous knotte of faithfull friendſhippe, as is aforeſaide: The force whereof doth chiefly appeare in this, that of ſo many kindes of Societies,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:9019:55"/>
which Nature hathe procured, it is onelye ſo ſtricte and rare, that it cannot be well poſſeſt of manye, but fewe in number, and that is two at the moſte, of whiche ſorte were <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Epheſtion, Titus</hi> and <hi>Giſippus, Pilades</hi> and <hi>Oreſtes, Damon</hi> and <hi>Pithias, Phocion</hi> and <hi>Nicocles,</hi> wyth <hi>Publius Scipio</hi> and <hi>Caius Lelius</hi> aforeſaid, whoſe liues were ſo deare of the one vnto the other, that for the moſt parte they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended whoſe death ſhould firſt celebrate their louing fame and memorie, ſuppoſing their glorious death to be better than vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie life with loſſe of friendſhippe. Such is the force of Loue, that it vanquiſheth tirants, conquereth the malice of the enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and reconcileth mortall foes vnto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect loue and amitie, inſomuche, that they are worthily ſaide to take the lighte of the Sunne oute of the worlde, whiche exclude friendſhippe from the life of men. And ſurely this ſo good a vertue is rather to bée perſwaded by example of life, than ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty reſoning.</p>
               <p>Although I cannot omit the great pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:9019:55"/>
of <hi>Virgil,</hi> who conſidering, that as friendſhippe is alwaies neceſſarie, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer oute of ſeaſon, ſo in trauaile moſte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, faineth vnto <hi>Aeneas</hi> in his long trauels &amp; perillous aduentures a faithfull friende and companion, whome he calleth <hi>Achates,</hi> of the worde <hi>Achos,</hi> which is ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe and care, ſignifying thereby, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo muche behoueth a Prince or Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, as to haue a care and eſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of his charge and companions in trauaile, whiche appeared in <hi>Aeneas,</hi> as well by the greate liberalitie he vſed, as occaſion and facultie ſerued, as alſo by the noble courteſie and comfortable wordes he gaue them in moſt daungerous aduerſitie.</p>
               <p>And for the laſte point to be touched, we wil (rather garniſhing the mind than hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the body) bathe oure heartes in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, arming our ſelues with Patience and Courteſie, and learne of him whiche iudgeth it the duetie of a ſtranger to apply his own buſineſſe, not regarding other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s affaires, and to bée nothing curious, and inquiſitiue in a ſtraunge common wealth,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:9019:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and as it becommeth not a Gentleman proudly to aduance himſelfe at home, ſo he muſt not ouerbaſhfully behaue himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade. And laſtly, there is nothing more commendable in any kind of attempt, then to procéede in the purpoſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende &amp; ful determination. For according to the Poet, <hi>Est aliquid prodi tenus ſi non datur vltra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus muche is hitherto ſpoken tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the neceſſarie order of Trauell, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, whoſoeuer doeth obſerue, (no doubte) he ſhall receiue and enioy the vnſpeakable pleaſures and commodities therin contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And with the accompliſhment of hys ſtudious minde be ſure at length to reape the rewarde whiche is painefully earned, and therefore moſte worthily obteyned by labour and Trauel.</p>
               <p>It reſteth now to ſhewe and ſette forth the highe treaſure and commodities of Trauell, whiche, bicauſe they are infinite, belonging as wel to the body as the mind, it is good to reſtraine ſo large a ſcope and ample matter, into a leſſe roomth and more compendious ſtile. Leauing then the reſte
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:9019:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
which is ſuperfluous, we will (ſtil fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring the minde) proſecute onely ſuche ioyfull treaſure and profitable pleaſure, as by vertuous actes of noble mindes alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die hath bene and is ſtill to be gotten and atteyned in Trauell. Wherein who doth not ſée howe ſure and ſkilfull a ſchoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres is experience, which not without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance and labour is reteyned? For if all thinges are atchieued by theſe thrée in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentes, that is, Arte, Vſe and Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, which are euen the guides of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, wée muſt of force ſéeke and embrace the ſame as the chiefe worker and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of this trade and facultie. And as arte is an ayde, &amp; helper of nature, ſo is experience the triall and perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of arte. For of experience commeth prudence, by prudence knowledge, by knowledge wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, than the which nothing is more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and diuine. Neyther would I haue any man ſuppoſe this to be ſpoken <hi>(Pingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minerua)</hi> as touchyng bare practiſe, which without knowledge as it is lame and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, ſo being directed by ſcience it wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:9019:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the perfection &amp; dignitie of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Let vs take for example the curious arte of Coſmographie, not ſtraying farre from the purpoſe, wherein if I ſhoulde take occaſion to talke of that parte of the worlde which is called <hi>Terra Habitabilis,</hi> the mayne lande inhabited, whereof ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the auncient wryters there are thrée partes, <hi>Europa, Africa,</hi> &amp; <hi>Aſia:</hi> the leaſte of them in quantitie is <hi>Europa,</hi> wherein we are conteyned, the head Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie whereof is <hi>Rome,</hi> nexte vnto that is <hi>Africke,</hi> wherein <hi>Carthage</hi> is chiefe, an earneſt follower and imitator of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre of <hi>Rome:</hi> but the greateſt parte is <hi>Aſia,</hi> whereof in tymes paſte the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Citie was <hi>Troye.</hi> And ſo to deſcribe the ſeas that deuide them all either from other, and yet enuironed rounde aboute with the ſame, myght I not well be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened to a blynde man iudgyng colours, that talke of ſuche thinges by heareſay, which I cannot as <hi>Occulatus testis</hi> parte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly witneſſe and reporte: Then let vs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay with <hi>Tully,</hi> that it is better to
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:9019:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
practiſe and doe aduiſedly, than to thinke and imagine neuer ſo wyſely. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: as I woulde withe my ſelfe able not to exhorte onelye, but to perſuade anye worthie and fitte perſons hereunto. So do I not hereby greatly animate or encorage the rude ſorte beyng ignorant of affayres, to ſuche kynde of Trauell: For euen as we ſée in the bodies of men diuers formes, whereby ſome are ſwyfte to runne, ſome light to leape, and other ſtrongly made to wreſtle: So lykewyſe the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the mynde are more in number, and therefore all men are not of one diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, which diuerſitie of natures full wiſely did <hi>Pithagoras</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, when he ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened the life of man vnto a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faire or ſolemne aſſembly, whereunto did ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſorte for earneſt occaſion of buſineſſe and affayres, and others to beholde the ſame, whome hée onelye iudged to haue the quyet lyfe, and all the reſt to be vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wyth continuall cares and perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the mynd: which tranquilitie and contented lotte of lyfe, he applied vnto the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:9019:58"/>
wyſe Philoſophers whom he ſuppoſed for this cauſe to be borne and brought foorth into the world, that they might by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation ſearch out the ſecretes of nature, and diſcerne the ſundrye diſpoſitions of men. Then if the nature of a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher or wyſe man be, to behold as it were in a glaſſe by ſpeculation, the hydden ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes of nature, of ſundrye one cauſe the dyuerſe effectes, and the variable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of mankynde, as is aforeſayd: Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye it behooueth theſe kynde of men very muche, if there be anye ſuche lefte, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the example of theyr aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, to beſtowe ſome tyme in Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle, whereby they myght the better profite others, and be better inſtructed them ſelues, whiche if they be the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the whole worlde to whome all countreys are in common, why ſhoulde they doubt to enioye that heritage or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony which others in tymes paſt dyd extort by wiſedome from Tyrannes? or if they them ſelues be perfect, why ſhoulde they childiſhly feare the corrupt maners
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:9019:58"/>
of others, but rather by the integritie of their lyues, ſéeke to reforme and inſtructe thoſe that be rude and imperfect. For this cauſe the diuine Philoſopher <hi>Plato,</hi> whoſe fame had ouerſpread all <hi>Greece,</hi> ſayled ofte into <hi>Scicilia,</hi> partly tendryng the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eſtate of that countrey, whoſe lot was often to be ruled and infeſted with Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes, whome he by the admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his wiſdom compelled vnto goodneſſe, and not foreſlowing his fame and honour thereby gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, perſeuered in the ſame, which ſemed by the ambitious anſwere he made vnto him that aſked, why (forſakyng his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and yelding him ſelfe vnto perils and dangers) he did neglect the building of his Tombe according to the maner of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, bicauſe ſaith he <hi>Primum nomen dein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vero monumenta:</hi> Firſt we muſt win ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, fame and good name, and thereby celebrate the woorthie Tombe and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of euerlaſtyng memorie. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted vnto the Court of <hi>Dioniſius</hi> the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt, which grudged at his fame and the increaſe of his honour, whiche <hi>Plato</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuyng,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:9019:59"/>
craued lycence to ſpeake with <hi>Dioniſius,</hi> which beyng graunted, he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thys kynde of reaſonyng: If your Maieſtie ſhould knowe of any man (ſaith <hi>Plato</hi>) that came into <hi>Scicilia</hi> wilfully bent to doe you ſome miſchiefe, which neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe for want of oportunitie fayled of his purpoſe, woulde you let hym eſcape ſcotfrée? wherunto the Kyng anſwered, no ſurely, for not onely the déede but the euyll intent is to be puniſhed. Then <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> vſed this obiection: but if another well diſpoſed perſon ſhoulde come hither to doe you a great good turne, &amp; cannot for want of oportunitie performe the ſame: were it reaſon hée ſhoulde be lykewyſe neglect and diſpiſed? The Kyng demaundyng who that was, euen <hi>Aeſchines</hi> ſayd <hi>Plato,</hi> a man for vertuous lyfe and ciuilitie of manners to be compared with any of the reſt of <hi>Socrates</hi> Schollers, who hauynge paſſed manye bitter ſtormes on the Sea, and other perilles to imparte hys wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge vnto thée, is hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto deſpyſed. This commodious ſpeach
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:9019:59"/>
of <hi>Plato</hi> ſo moued the Tyraunt <hi>Dioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> that whereas before hée diſdeyned, now he embraced <hi>Plato,</hi> and was earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected towardes <hi>Aeſchines.</hi> Thus we ſée, that both the déedes and words of wiſe men directed by vertue, are wonderfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anacharſis</hi> the <hi>Scithian,</hi> ſo much affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the deſire of knowledge, that he tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyled vnto <hi>Athens,</hi> onelye to heare the wiſedome of <hi>Solon,</hi> who at that tyme flouryſhed amongeſt the <hi>Athenians,</hi> in ſo muche as commyng thyther, hée bolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly badde hym ſelfe to dynner wyth <hi>Solon,</hi> and ſent hym worde that <hi>Anacharſis</hi> the <hi>Scithian</hi> coueted both to be his gueſt and hys Scholler: to whome <hi>Solon</hi> aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweared by hys ſeruaunt, that hoſpitalitie was wonte to be amongeſt men in theyr owne countrey, meanyng that betwéene the <hi>Athenians</hi> &amp; <hi>Scithians</hi> there was no ſuch right of cuſtome: at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which anſwere ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe he entred into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of <hi>Solon,</hi> ſaying, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was euen nowe in hys owne countrey, &amp; therefore ought to be receyued as a gueſt, wherwith <hi>Solon</hi> being greatly
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:9019:60"/>
delighted, receiued hym courteouſly euen vnto faythfull familiaritie and friende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp, perceyuyng by the firſt wordes hée ſpake, his philoſophicall mynde, whych iudged it hys natyue ſoile, whereſoeuer hée was well entertayned: whiche cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie towardes <hi>Anatharſis,</hi> I ſuppoſe that <hi>Solon</hi> vſed the rather, doyng that vnto others whiche hée wiſhed vnto hym ſelfe: for not long tyme after, ſcarce ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſatiſfied, eyther wyth the honour and dignitie ſo hardlye deſerued, or with the ſlender reward &amp; colde conſideration of the <hi>Athenians</hi> towards him, which aſwel by wiſedome &amp; ſadneſſe, as in fained fury and madneſſe, had profited his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the ſame in open place, did ſodeinely from thence ſaile forth into <hi>Egypte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And laſtly, amongſt Philoſophers, who doeth not highly commende the contented mynde of <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> which after long peregrination and traueyle in the ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching out of knowledge, at his returne founde his patrimony and poſſeſſions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, &amp; his countrey almoſt deſert, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:9019:60"/>
at béeing little moued with impatience or ſorowe, ſayde, if theſe had not periſhed, my ſelfe had not bin ſaued. Oh Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall minde, armed with Socraticall patience, which eſtéemed not the value of riches, in reſpecte of the treaſure of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor bewayled the loſſe of goodes, whereby he founde the diuine knowledge of wiſdome. And thus it appeareth, that thoſe things are proſperous, whiche vnto vs ſometime ſéeme infortunate, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywiſe, that whiche is accompted for lucre, may be turned into loſſe. And for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> experience of knowledge in trauell, thys may be ſufficient. Nowe haue we to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider chiefely, the valiant actes, and adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of noble minds atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted by courage and magnanimitie. And eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly breaketh out <hi>Hercules</hi> that heroycall wight,<note place="margin">Hercules.</note> as worthily chalenging vnto him ſelfe the principalitie of all the powers in the worlde, whoſe actes &amp; attempts, as for antiquitie they be ſuddainely worne out of noble mens Halles, ſo if they were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>piled togither in one volume, I doubt,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:9019:61"/>
that a greate manye woulde ſooner ſpende their whole time in contemplation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, than be by emulation moued, although not to the like enterpriſes, nor yet to ſuch like worthy exerciſe, in defence of theyr Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ntrey. This was <hi>Hercules Thebanus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Amphitrio,</hi> whiche hauing by miſfortune ſlayne his brother, fledde from <hi>Tyrintho,</hi> vnto <hi>Thebes,</hi> where it fortuned this <hi>Hercules</hi> to be borne, and after that he had there ſhewed the firſt proofe of hys ſtrength and proweſſe, in defence of that Citie, beſéeged by them of <hi>Minia,</hi> forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with deliuered the Sea aboute <hi>Spayne</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> from a number of Pirats, in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall memorie whereof, they cauſed two greate Rockes to be ſet vp in the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt corners of <hi>Spayne</hi> and <hi>Afrike,</hi> whiche at this daye are called <hi>Hercules</hi> Pillers: from whence he paſſing into <hi>Aſia,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered and ſlew <hi>Laomedon</hi> King of <hi>Troy,</hi> but deliuered the poſſeſſion of the Kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to <hi>Priamus</hi> his ſonne. What ſhould I ſpeake of thoſe twelue high aduentures whiche were called <hi>Hercules</hi> laboures,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:9019:61"/>
which would carie more wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> credit to be pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced? And next enſueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high courage of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, whome neither Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey nor kingdome, Monarch or Empire, no not the wide circuite of the whole world, was wel able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teine, for béeyng but <hi>.20.</hi> yeares of age, he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame with an armie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by his father <hi>Philip,</hi> which was in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber <hi>.32000.</hi> foteme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and <hi>.4500.</hi> horſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hauing no Captayne vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> age of <hi>.60.</hi> yeares, bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not in their legges, but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> force of armes they ſhuld place y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hope of victory. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt yere of his raigne, he was ſaluted Emperour of <hi>Greece,</hi> but bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned of the <hi>Thebanes,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould thinke him in courage not inferiour vnto <hi>Hercules,</hi> he va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citie by force of armes, deſtroyed it, &amp; ſold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people for pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants. In vaine it were to rehearſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties &amp; townes, ſith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treys &amp; kingdoms were almoſt infinite which he conquered. And comming firſte into <hi>Aſia,</hi> he ſubdued the <hi>Perſians,</hi> and vanquiſhed all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions extending vnto <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rigia</hi> and <hi>Scythia,</hi>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:9019:62"/>
where mette with hym <hi>Darius</hi> wyth a mightie army at <hi>Iſſus,</hi> but his legges bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſerued than his armes, for béeyng put to flight, he left his mother <hi>Sigambris,</hi> his wife, and hir ſiſters behind, to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with <hi>Alexander,</hi> whome notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he moſt honourably intreated, and courteouſly enterteyned. After thys, he was honourably receyued at <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and conquered all <hi>Egipt,</hi> where en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the Temple of <hi>Hamon,</hi> he was worſhipped of the Prieſts for the ſonne of <hi>Iupiter.</hi> From thence he trauelled into <hi>India,</hi> where he had a greate conflict wyth <hi>Codrus</hi> their King, which came with <hi>.60.</hi> other Princes, and foure hundred Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantes, with ſtrong munition on theyr backes, againſte <hi>Alexander,</hi> and yet was taken and reſtored againe vnto his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. This done, he ſent forth his Nauie into the Eaſt Occean Seas, to ſearche if there were yet any other part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quered. The long trauels, &amp; hard adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tures of <hi>Aeneas,</hi> which by the wrath of <hi>Iuno</hi> wer hardned, &amp; by the fauourable
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:9019:62"/>
aſpect of his mother <hi>Venus</hi> lightened, I leaue vntouched, as vnknowen to fewe or none, omitting likewiſe the ſondrye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictes of <hi>Hector</hi> and <hi>Achilles, Hanniball,</hi> and <hi>Scipio,</hi> with others infinite, &amp; laſtly, the noble actes of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> which dyd extend euen vnto our owne natiue Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of <hi>Britayne,</hi> where I can not let paſſe the noble entrance of <hi>Brute</hi> the Troiane Captayne, and firſte Conquerour of thys land, then inhabited with Giants and ſauage people, as it appeareth ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the iuſt record of Chronographers.</p>
               <p>This noble <hi>Brutus,</hi> ſonne of <hi>Siluius,</hi> whoſe father was <hi>Aſcanius,</hi> not content to liue as a ſubiect in <hi>Greece,</hi> whoſe aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters had bin the Princes of the worlde, gathered togither an army of the Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians, and furniſhed themſelues with Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Shippes, in deſpite of their Kyng <hi>Pandraſus,</hi> whiche at the firſte refuſed gently to ſupporte them in their voyage, but afterwarde was contente to yéelde to the requeſt of the Troyans, and the more willingly, for that he doubted their force
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:9019:63"/>
and worthy proweſſe; for that <hi>Pandraſus</hi> the King, was content to giue his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in mariage with <hi>Brutus,</hi> with a boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull dower, torwardes the furniſhing of his aduentures, and forthwith <hi>Brutus,</hi> with his army, called from <hi>Greece,</hi> into the Ilande of <hi>Leogitin,</hi> where <hi>Brute</hi> conſulted with an Oracle, from whence, after ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne ſacrifice done, he receyued thys an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere according to <hi>Cambrius.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Brute, ſub occaſum ſolis, trans gallica regna</l>
                  <l>Inſula in oceano eſt, vndi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> clauſa mari:</l>
                  <l>Inſula in oceano eſt, habitata Gigantibus olim,</l>
                  <l>Nunc deſerta quidem, gentibus aptatuis.</l>
                  <l>Hanc pete, nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tibi ſedes erit illa perennis,</l>
                  <l>Hic fiet natis altera Troia tuis.</l>
                  <l>Hic de prole tua reges naſcentur, &amp; ipſis,</l>
                  <l>Totius terrae ſubditus orbis erit.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Which Verſes are thus Engli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by <hi>Holinſhead.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Brute</hi> farre by Weaſt, beyond the gallicke land, is found</l>
                  <l>An Ile, which with the Occean ſeas incloſed is about,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:9019:63"/>Where Gia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts dwelt ſomtimes, but now is deſert grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
                  <l>Moſt mete wher y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maiſt pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſelf with all thy route.</l>
                  <l>Make thither wards with ſpede, for ther y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt find out</l>
                  <l>An euer during ſeate, and <hi>Troy</hi> ſhall riſe anewe</l>
                  <l>Vnto thy race, of whome ſhall Kings be borne no doubt</l>
                  <l>That with their mighty force y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world ſhal hole ſubdue.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And héerewith <hi>Brutus,</hi> glad to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued ſo certayne an aunſwere from the Oracle, departed to hys Shyppes, and came along the coaſtes of <hi>Afrike,</hi> where hée mette wyth the reſt of the Troians that came away with <hi>Anthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> whoſe Captayne was <hi>Corineus,</hi> and ſo ioyning both armyes togyther, they came into the coaſtes of <hi>Britayne,</hi> where after ſundrye conflictes had wyth the Giantes there inhabiting, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the ſauage people, and long tyme poſſeſſed the land in quiet peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitie, as appeareth more at large in the Chronicle: ſo that we maye ſée what the ſtate of Countreys are and haue bene, whyche by the paynefull tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels of worthye Conqueroures, haue bin from time to time of barbarous people
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:9019:64"/>
broughte to a moſt ciuill gouernemente, whyche kynde of trauell beſides an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of pleaſaunt commodities, hath in it ſelfe ſo cloſely conteyned a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne kynde of naturall inclination, that it cauſeth diuers men of ſundrye myndes to affecte the vſe and experience thereof. For as the Sunne hath ſundry good gifts of grace, workyng diuers effects, ſo the myndes of the ſtudious are not all gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned withe one kynde of vertue, whyche cauſeth them to be diuerſly affected, ſome with deſire of knowledge, ſome wyth ſtrange ſightes of auntient monumentes, ſome with aduentures in finding out of vnknowen Countreys and the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities thereof, and other with manye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynges are delighted, as in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the languages, ſearching out the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes of nature, &amp; diſcouering the maners of menne, and cuſtomes of Countreys, whyche as they are all to be allowed, ſo me thynkes that kynde of indeuoure, whyche procéedeth of the deſire of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to bée the beſt worthy of commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:9019:64"/>And to conclude with <hi>Tullie,</hi> whome firſte and laſte for honours ſake I name, I ſuppoſe, that the knowledge of ſecreates and wonders, are moſte profitable to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe the ſteadfaſte felicitie and happineſſe of mans life: which, as it is the marke and ſcope whereat al men do ſhoote, as no doubt all thinges are referred to an ende, ſo it commes to paſſe, that after lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g trauel and peregrinations abroade, we ſhall returne towards our owne natiue ſoile, with a ful contentation to beholde oure kinſfolkes, friendes, and companions, and finally, by this means armed with experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, be more able to perſeuer in the ſundry ſeruice of our moſte noble Prince and famous Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:9019:65"/>
               <head>Of Stabilitie.</head>
               <head>CHAP. 9.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto euery liuing thing Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath giuen a prouident care, to ſéeke and maintaine the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities of life, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in the leaſte creatures of all is commonly moſt manifeſt to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. And firſt we ſée the carefull proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the little Emites, whiche, (as it is cunningly deſcribed of <hi>Virgil</hi>) in the colde winter ſeaſon, are aſſembled togither in manner of an army, when they moſte buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apply themſelues to ſpoile the heapes of corne, ſcattered here and there in the wyde fieldes vnder the mole hilles, and ſuche like huge mountaines, moſte paineful and troubleſome for their heauie carriage. And wide themſelues they diſperſe all the daye long, gathering vppe their loades vntill towardes the euening, when they al méete
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:9019:65"/>
togither, marching homewardes valiantly like victors, ſome vnder burden groning with their booties, ſome ſhouing with the might of their ſhoulders the greater ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelles of heauie graine, ſome (chaunging burden) chéere their fellowes ouerloaden, and ſome lighted of their labours, come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde to ſuruey the traine, correcting ſome of ſlouth, and ſetting al thinges in good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And nowe the wayes are worne with waight of ſuche heauie cariadge, and euery path is moiſtned with the ſweate of theyr dayly laboures, vntill they come home to their own dwelling place, where they ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſtowe their prouiſion afield, to ſupply the néede preſent, as alſo to ſupporte the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie which by dearth or famine mighte happe in time to come hereafter.</p>
               <p>And thus we ſée the prouidence of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in this ſmall creature to be wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. And not onelye Prouidence is graunted vnto theſe, but euen in manye other vnreaſonable creatures, we find ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie ſpeciall giftes &amp; prudent qualities (if I
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:9019:66"/>
may ſo call them) whiche in effect ſéeme to imitate the knowledge &amp; perfection of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. To witte, the Foxe which in craft ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celles all other beaſtes, euen in this pointe is chiefly noted of Subtiltie, that he neuer prayes neare home, ſo that commonlye he doth moſte harme where he is leaſte ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. The Hedgehog ſéemes to haue iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Aſtronomie, whiche ſtops his caue againſte any te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt that is comming. The little Bée giueth a ſingular example of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie, whiche out of euery dower gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſome ſwéeteneſſe. The Nightingale w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> a ſwéete note giueth warning to be watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. What a gift hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hound in ſmelling? what courage hathe a horſe in trauelling? howe farre doeth the Lynx excell all other beaſtes in ſight? and laſtely, what a kinde of highe courage is in the Lion, whiche fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth thoſe that fawne, and deſtroyeth anye thing that doeth withſtande? Theſe and ſuche like a number of brute beaſtes, ſhewe and ſette foorth the excellencie of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures giftes, and chiefly in that euerye one followeth his naturall inclination accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:9019:66"/>
to his owne kinde. Then howe much ought men (being ſpiritually indued wyth reaſon and vnderſtanding) buſily to apply themſelues in the maintainaunce of lyfe, and ſeriouſly to beſtowe their time accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the quantitie and value of their ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, it is eaſie to be gathered. But accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the opinion of <hi>Cicero,</hi> there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo doubtfull and vncertaine in the iudgement of a yong man, as ſtedfaſtly to choſe what trade of life to vndertake. And true it is, for (beſides that the trades and faculties of life are diuers) there are alſo ſuche an infinite number of conceites, and fantaſtical opinions, which vexe the minds of vnſkilful youth, that herewith the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Reaſon is blinded, the election of Witte troubled, and the ſenſes of Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding quite ouerthrowen.</p>
               <p>For, if at ſome times, being better ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed, we fall into deliberation of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, we are as ſoone in one ſentence, as ſoone in an other, and howe manye vaines, ſo manye vanities: no otherwiſe than as an emptie Shippe vnburdened, and withoute
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:9019:67"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:9019:67"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:9019:68"/>
equall baliſte is taſte too farre vppon the boiſterous billowes of the ſwelling Seas, and lightly carried hither and thither with the leaſte winde that blowes, vntill at length by ſome ſodaine ſtorme and hideous tempeſt it is throwen headlong vppon the ſhelfe of harde <hi>Semphlegades,</hi> ſo is the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkilfull minde of youth not equally pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the ballaunce of Experience, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drawen into ſundrie opinions by the fonde allurementes of deceitfull Follie, vntill at laſte for want of Stabilitie and good Gouernment, it is commonlye ſubiect to the gripes of miſfortune, and ſodaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye fallen into the ſnares of ſhamefull miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief.</p>
               <p>And this we ſée by dayly experience, that if one man bée moued with common pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, a number be delighted with ſelfe loue and priuate pleaſure: if Vertue drawe ſome vnto goodneſſe, Vice driueth manye more vnto miſchiefe: if Reaſon perſwade this, Fanſie forceth vnto that: if Witte weye one waye, Will wreſteth another
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:9019:68"/>
waye, and ſome (as <hi>Horace</hi> witneſſeth) are ſo wauering and inconſtante, that not life at all can like them, no degrées of eſtate can content them, and with no kinde of fortune they wil be ſatiſfied. Kinges are troubled wyth cares (as they ſaye) Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure haunted with Enuie, no maieſtie in meane eſtate, in pouertie nothing but néede and penurie, ſingle life is ſolitarie, and mariage is ſubiect to an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of troubles, ſo that it is vnlike for theſe men to be reſolued vppon anye trade or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, which can fanſie no kinde of eſtate: and it is no meruaile, though craftes and baſe cunning be contemned, when the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſciences, and heauenly wiſedome it ſelfe are vtterly deſpiſed and forlorne. A harde worlde you will ſaye, when Diuinitie is ſuſpected, a ſhrewde caſe when the lawes are neglected, and a frowarde time when phiſicke is reiected: to learne true ſpeach is but trifling, Eloquence is little better than Loquacitie, Logick is nothing elſe but liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſnes, ſwéet melodie is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſloth,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:9019:69"/>
in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring men now a daies ſtande for ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers: meaſuring of land is better for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that build &amp; purchaſe (which are few) than for ſuche as waſte and ſell (which are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye:) and for the iudgement of the Starres it is thoughte to be vaine and vncertaine. Againe the trade of Merchandize ſtandes vppon haphazarde: Citizens are for the moſte parte vnconſcionable: the countrey life is clowniſhe: warrefare is harde and daungerous: and trauel is coſtly and peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: So that any kinde of life to theſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes is loathſome: but they are no Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunts, they will not be Subiecte to ſeruile bondage, whereas indéede by this meanes they are frée from Libertie, for, what is Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie? but to haue frée choice and election of things pleaſaunt, profitable, and honeſt, the vſe whereof, if it make to the felicitie and happineſſe of life, then ſuche as wante the commodities of the ſame, muſte néedes be accompted vnfortunate.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, if it were granted vnto them, that in all things there is abuſe, ſhould we
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:9019:69"/>
therefore vſe nothing? the waye to vice is pleaſaunt and plaine, ſhould we therefore runne headlong into miſchiefe? the hill of vertue is hard to clymbe, and therfore ſhal we be ſlouthfull? to be ſhort, the times are chaunged, the manners altered, and the whole world is vncertaine: and ſhould we therefore not liue, or neglect the neceſſarye commodities of life? then might we iuſtly giue place vnto brute beaſtes, whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in that point excéedeth our reaſon, and whoſe ſmall prouidence ouerreacheth our déepe vnderſtanding.</p>
               <p>But to leaue theſe wandring wittes (whiche are conſtante in nothing but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaintie) of ſuche as meane to incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate themſelues, and to become profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table members of the common wealth: I ſuppoſe theſe thrée pointes in the choyſe of life to be chiefely conſidered, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally followed: And firſt that we enter into the iuſt contemplation of our owne natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diſpoſition, and the rather applye oure ſelues to that life, wherevnto nature is chiefely enclyned, for according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:9019:70"/>
                  <hi>a good beginning, makes a good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> and ſurely nothing is well begun, nor like happily to procéede, wherevnto nature is not conſenting. Secondly, that we ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlye follow that kinde of practiſe or ſtudie, whiche in youth hath bene grafted by inſtruction, and by longeſt continuance in vs accuſtomed: And thirdly, not ouer haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nor ouertimely to addict our ſelues to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye one kinde of calling, but that we maye be remoued vnto an other, if better occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with oportunitie ſhould ſerue: for no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſo ſteadfaſtly grounded in anye degrées of eſtate, but that (by the wrath of fortune) he is made ſubiect to change and alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of life. And touching the firſt point, ſurelye it ſéemes to be neceſſarie, that nature ſhold giue hir verdict in the frée choyce of facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and trade of life: For as in a common aſſemblie and Parlament (where conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and deliberation is had of matters y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are doubtful and neceſſarie) al mens opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are hearde, and no mans voyce is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, in ſo muche as the ſentence or ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (pronounced by one onelye man) is drawen for the moſt part out of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:9019:70"/>
conſent of all the reſte: So in the choyce of this (which ſucceſſiuelye ioyneth vs in the corporation of the other) we can not but iniurie our ſelues, in reſtrayning the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Nature, too muche leaning to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of reaſon, and counſayle of others: And it ſhoulde ſéeme rather in this pointe more profitable to forſake witte than wil, more commendable to leaue friendes than fanſie, and more neceſſarie to obey nature than reaſon: for if nature haue not graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſtrength, it is not witte that may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the harde laboure and waightye force of wreſtling: if courage ſerue not to aſſault, it helpeth not by pollicy to ſuccour. And it is vaine for a cripple to contende in ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning, ſcornful for the crow to thinke hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe beautifull: who is ſo madde that wyl ſet an Aſſe to learne Muſicke, or ſo blynde that calles a Buſſard to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lure? what auai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it to ſow in the ſandes, and make fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes in the ſea? and what pleaſure is it to put on a maſtye at a Deare, &amp; a Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounde at a Beare? Surely no more fitte and conueniente is it for a man to liue
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:9019:71"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to his own natural diſpoſition: It is harde to ſtriue againſt the ſtreame, hop againſte an hill, and ſpurne againſte the prick. So the force of nature is inuincible, which though ſhe be reſiſted manye times for good cauſe, yet ſhe will neuer ſuffer hir ſelf to be vanquyſhed, and quite ouercome. And is it not reaſon, that ſhe which is the Authour of life, ſhoulde giue counſayle in the order and good maintenance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame? ſhould not the mother inſtruct hir childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? or doth not the opinion of the Iudge beare chiefe credite in the cauſe? yes no doubte, and ſo muche the ſooner to be accepted, by howe muche the more it ſéemeth to giue light, and chiefe euidence to the truth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter: but you will ſay, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt &amp; therfore not méete to ſit in place of iudgement: in déed this reaſon is not light, in other matters which ſéemeth harder to be confuted, than maintayned, &amp; if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequente be true: I coulde wiſhe it were nowadayes generally practiſed and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: but in this caſe I denye that nature of it ſelf is corrupt, nor vicious, but cuſtome,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:9019:71"/>
nor hurtefull by anye meanes vnto it ſelfe, and therfore not to be refuſed: and it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that diſcorde is in all things the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of miſchiefe: wée ſée that a kingdome diuided wythin it ſelfe cannot ſtande, much leſſe the man (that is continuallye vexed with contrarie thoughtes and affections) in his actes and operations can proſper. Ther be diuerſe parts and members of the bodie, but the minde guideth them all into one kinde of motion. Let vs take for an example that honourable ſtate of mariage (whiche by reaſon ſéemeth to be the firſte ſteppe of Stabilitie) for compaſſed by lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and aduiſemente, it reſembleth the ioyes of heauen, and raſhly enterpriſed, it is equall with the tormentes of Hell: it is only the treaſure or diſcommodities, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity or aduerſity, the only felicity or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſſe of life: wherein truely there is nothing ſo daungerous, as the inequalitie of eſtates in ſuch a ſtedfaſt knot and firme coniunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of two bodies: for what likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of condition can there be betwéen two of diuerſe diſpoſitions? or what conſent or
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:9019:72"/>
agréeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in ij. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie natures? whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one ſhal be lowly and the other lofty, one ambitious y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other curteous, one chaſt the other incontinent, one couetous and the other by nature churliſhe. And as the Wolfe cannot leaue to be rauenous, nor vnthankefull ſwine learne to be curteous: ſo the haughty Lion is merciful by kind, &amp; the ſilly Lamb by nature innocent. But we ſée there is hard familiaritie betwéene any of theſe creatures, bycauſe their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures be contrarie, and therfore commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly they ſéeke one anothers deſtruction. And as vnequal oxen can not wel drawe togither in one yoake: ſo the match is marde where the mates are not like diſpoſed, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, nothing els proſperous <hi>(inuita Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerua)</hi> to ſay, nature not conſenting. And now to the ſecond point of this deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there belongeth a dutiful regard in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe ſchoolemaſtreſſe experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vnto whoſe diſcipline &amp; inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wée haue bin longeſt accuſtomed: For it is an olde ſaying, <hi>
                     <hi>Rome</hi> was not builded in one daye,</hi> neither is any ſerious matter to be atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:9019:72"/>
with ouermuche haſte, &amp; nothing is ſo hardly won, which is more eaſily loſt, the ſtrong hold or fortreſſe, whoſe bulwarkes ſéeme to be inuincible, at length with hard &amp; perilous adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tures is entred, &amp; yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps againe by ſlight policies, in a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t loſt and recouered. And next vnto Nature hir ſelf, Cuſtome chale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth a large prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue, whiche (in proceſſe of time) maketh hirſelfe almoſt equall w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Nature in force &amp; conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. For, if we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world (which is by antiquitie of times principally directed in good things) we ſhal find almoſt nothing in ſo large an Empire that is no ſubiect to the rule of cuſtome: firſt the generall fruite and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of kinde, is by cuſtome naturallye increaſed &amp; maintained, by cuſtome Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and kings are crowned, by cuſtome Knightes and Lordes created, and by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome Iuſtice adminiſtred, truth exalted, dueties regarded, Deſertes rewarded, mighte encouraged, and to be ſhorte, all kynde of good vertues eaſilye attayned and worthyly embraced: the ſeruauntes of cuſtome, are theſe thrée, Arte, Vſe,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:9019:73"/>
and exerciſe, and as theſe are by cuſtome ſpecially maintayned, ſo by them al things alſo are vſually atchieued, and from theſe commeth alſo experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which in any facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or trade of life is moſt neceſſarie: and herein appeareth the imperfection of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkilfull youth, whiche being ignoraunte of affaires, ſometimes enterpriſe to reach (by a ſuperficiall kind of knowledge) vnto the practiſe of high myſteries, too far aboue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſlight conſideration of their gréene capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and in the ende (in rewarde of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfayte ſkill and preſumption, and fained holyneſſe) they receiue the iuſt puniſhment of ſhameful reproch and confuſion. It is a common prouerb amongſt vs, he that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in haſt, ſhal repent at leaſure: &amp; indéed a man can not be too chary in that choyce, nor too circumſpect in electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that trade wherein he meanes ſteadfaſtlye to run the whole courſe of his life: if we doe entende to win friendſhip with any man, ſée howe circumſpect we are in finding out his vain, how curious in conſidering his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions, and how nyce in fauouring his nature: but
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:9019:73"/>
doth it not ſtand vs more vpon (in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of life) to behold our owne proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and conditions, for no man is borne wiſe, nor any man can ſuddainely become happie: but euen as in the ſpring time, the naturall ſappe and moyſture of the trée breaketh out firſt into the blooming buds, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> buds into bloſſoms, and then fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms, by little and little into a more har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſubſtance (whereby it is better able to withſtand the hurtfull blaſtes, and bitter colde) vntill at laſt it ſoftneth agayne, by the vertue of the Sunne, when it commes to the perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ripeneſſe of the fruite: ſo the naturall diſpoſition of mankinde, is firſt moued with affection, to ſéeke know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, then cunning is deſirous to imitate the practiſe of vertues, by the example of others that were famous: and thus expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience by cuſtome, bringeth a man at laſt to the full perfection of wiſedome, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the regard of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall experience, in the choyſe of mans life, is moſt neceſſary. Thirdly, it behoueth man to be armed at all aſſayes, againſt the change of tymes,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:9019:74"/>
and mutabilitie of fortune, for nothing in this life is ſtadfaſt &amp; permanent: no coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey ſo rich, that warres hath not waſted: no quiet peace and tranquility ſo durable, that diſcord hath not diſſolued: no beautie ſo diuine, which by cloudes of care is not eclipſed: no courage ſo ſtoute, whiche by crooked age is not qualified: and laſtly, no mirth, no ioy, no pleaſure, no paſtime, no loue, no luſt, no kind of commoditie ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and permanent, whiche is not by ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, care, troubles, enuie, wrath, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, or miſfortune, made ſubiect to ſome change and alteration: ſo that the minde is only conſtant, whiche is content, &amp; that man ſéemeth moſt happie, that is patient: &amp; as riches, health, honour alone, without ſingular vertues, maketh not fortunate, ſo truth, courage, equitie, bountie, &amp; ſuche like, without perfect reſt, and contentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the mind, cannot lay the plot &amp; foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Stabilitie: for can we call hym riche that is couetous? or courteous y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is proude? or noble that is ſcorneful? no more can he be conſtant y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is furious and fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall:
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:9019:74"/>
neyther ought any man to eſtéeme the choiſe of faculties &amp; trades of liuing to be the onely ſuertie &amp; ſtedfaſtneſſe of life. Sith that the giftes of nature and fortune both richlye poſſeſſed are not ſufficient to the maintenance of felicitie: for he is not to be accompted happie, that is not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and perfecte of him ſelfe, and coueteth more to encreaſe, or feares any thing to be diminiſhed: And therefore <hi>Solon</hi> (beyng demaunded of the rich Kyng <hi>Craeſus</hi> what letted him to be called happie) anſwered, bicauſe he was yet alyue: meaning that no eſtate of lyfe is frée from the bondage and yoake of ſorrowe, for neither Kings nor Princes can aſſure them ſelues ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly to ſtande in the good grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of fortune: which by the example of <hi>Policrates</hi> was manifeſtly prooued, whoſe eſtate was long tyme proſperous, and ſo beautifully furniſhed with health, wealth, and pleaſure, that he began to be at defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce with fortune hir ſelfe, and diſpiſed the fawning fauour of <hi>Neptune</hi> that ſent him his Kyng againe in the bowels of a
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:9019:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Fiſhe, which he had before wilfully caſte into the ſea (being of great price) to trye the friendſhyppe of fortune. But as the Sunne being at the higheſt, muſt néedes decline by his naturall courſe againe. So the blinde Goddeſſe (whoſe lookes are like vnto brittle glaſſe that is not ſo bryght but it is aſſoone broken) now beganne to ſhake the chaire of proude <hi>Policrates,</hi> and aſſoone ouerwhelmed him in the paynes of helf, whom ſhée had before hoyſed vp into the ioyes and pleaſures of heauen: For of a King he became a captiue, and of a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie man a moſt miſerable wretche, and ſo died at miſchiefe. And thus we ſée by thys onelye example which maye be matched with innumerable of like ſort, that no life is certaine, none eſtate ſtedfaſt, and no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition nor any kynde of callyng without continuall cares, troubles, and aflictions. And therfore I conclude, that Pacience is the ſtrongeſt armour of proofe to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the ſpitefull force of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant and variable Fortune.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:9019:75"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
